<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!--<DOCTYPE tei2 SYSTEM "/itssgml/sgmlstd/dtds/ammem2/ammem2_xml.dtd"> -->
<!--
<!DOCTYPE tei2
  SYSTEM "/itssgml/sgmlstd/dtds/ammem2/ammem2axml_noURLs.dtd"
[<!ENTITY % images SYSTEM "BLA BLA BLA">
%images;]>
-->


<tei2>
   <teiheader type="text" creator="Manuscript Division, Library of Congress" status="new" date.created="02/01/2006">
   </teiheader>
   <text type="manuscript">
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0001">0001</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
      <body>
         <div>

<p>NATIONAL MUSEUM OF AFRICAN AMERICAN HISTORY AND CULTURE</p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p>Civil Rights History Project</p>
<p></p>
<p>Smithsonian Institute's National Museum of African American History &amp; Culture and the Library of Congress, 2011</p>
<p></p>
<p>Mildred Bond Roxborough oral history interview</p>
<p></p>
<p>conducted by Julian Bond</p>
<p></p>
<p>in New York, New York, Oct. 29, 2010</p>
<p></p>
<p>[START afc2010039_crhp0002_mv1.WMV]</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  She never stopped</p>
<p>01:00:04  talking.</p>
<p>FEMALE VOICE:  Ms. Roxborough [phonetic], Mr. Bond, I'm recording.  Begin the interview.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Ready to go?</p>
<p>FEMALE VOICE:  Yes, sir.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Ms. Roxborough, you were born into an African American family that was aware of the need to do what was necessary to improve the quality of their daily lives.</p>
<p>01:00:32      Can you share with us how your family made changes in their lives to improve their situation?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Well, we lived in one of the three counties in the State of Tennessee, in which blacks did not vote.  One of the things my parents felt which would be of paramount importance was to get the right to vote.  They proceeded to campaign for that purpose by getting</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0002">0002</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>01:00:55 other people in the community to join them to go to the county courthouse to register to vote.  That was a primary ingredient.  This is before</p>
<p>01:01:13 they organized a branch of the NACP.  Of course, they also felt that the community of blacks in the county--Hayward County was the county in which we lived.  The county was Brownsville in which I was born.</p>
<p>Of course, they felt that it was important to organize our black citizens because they outnumbered the</p>
<p>01:01:42 white citizens about 3 to 1.  If they could marshal the black citizens in greater strength, they could change the quality of our lives to some extent by exercising political power.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Did you ever hear your parents talk about organizing the first NAACP chapter in Brownsville?  Did you ever hear them discuss it?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Yes.</p>
<p>01:02:05 INTERVIEWER:  What did they have to say?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Well, they said that we needed to have people who would be able to withstand the pressures which</p>
<p>01:02:14 they anticipated would be applied when they started formally organizing a group together instead of having an individual who would join them on certain occasions.  In order to do this, at that time, as I recall, Walter White was executive secretary of the NAACP.  I would hear his name frequently, saying we've got to get Walter White to authorize a charter</p>
<p>01:02:55 for our unit.  Then they rode away to get enough information about the number of people who would be required.</p>
<p>There was much discussion when I was a youngster.  I suppose about this time I was about 7 years of age, having been reading The Crisis because they subscribed to it.  I was well aware of what the NAACP was in</p>
<p>01:03:21 my own perspective.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  You were 9 years old when you first became involved with NAACP.  What led you to be willing to sell The Crisis, to sell</p>
<p>01:03:33 subscriptions?</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0003">0003</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Both my parents would teach us.  My mother, there were three of us, of which I was the youngest.  My mother or my father virtually every evening before I went to bed would read poetry, excerpts from history, and events to my sisters.  I would be sitting on my mother's lap.  Oftentimes, in reading</p>
<p>01:04:01 poetry, she would quote to them saying that this is a piece by Langston Hughes, which was published in The Crisis Magazine.  Of course, I wanted to know what The Crisis was after having heard her say that so often.  She said, "You'll see it.  It's here on the desk," or wherever.  I would start looking for The Crisis after hearing my mother mention the</p>
<p>01:04:24 fact that they actually were reading excerpts from things that appeared therein.  That's how I learned about The Crisis.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  How'd you come to sell</p>
<p>01:04:33 subscriptions?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Well, I noticed they had in some ad in the paper indicating that subscriptions were available.  I said one day, "Can I write to Roy Wilkins [phonetic]," who was the editor of The Crisis, "and ask him if I can sell The Crisis?"  After all, if you're going to have a chapter of the NAACP, then--my</p>
<p>01:05:01 language wasn't as it is today, as you can appreciate--they said, "By all means, but you must write the letter yourself."  I said I'll do that, so I did.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Did he write back?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  I heard--I don't know if it was from him--saying we will be glad to have you sell The Crisis Magazine.  In any event, it was typed, but it had his signature</p>
<p>01:05:23 on it and under his name it said editor.  I was so proud to get that letter from the editor of The Crisis.  I was beside myself.</p>
<p>01:05:35 INTERVIEWER:  I bet.  Can you share any details with us about what happened to your father as a result of his civil rights activities in 1939?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Well, by 1939 the branch had been organized.  He was the president and my mother was secretary.  During those intervening years, my father had been arrested</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0004">0004</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>01:06:01 and taken to jail a few times, but not formally charged.  He was usually let go.  However, one evening he was brought home having been rather badly beaten.  The sheriff and a deputy--anyway, they were law enforcement officials--brought him home and opened the front door, which wasn't locked because in those days you didn't lock your door until you went</p>
<p>01:06:32 to bed at night I think.  I was home alone.  My mother was at a meeting.</p>
<p>They brought him in and dumped him on the couch really.  They said, "Take care of your pa.  He's been hurt.  If</p>
<p>01:06:45 he had not had connections, he would be in jail."  I was of course frightened.  I was about 9 at the time.  When my mother came home, I said to her these two men brought them home and they said to me if he did not have connections, he would be in jail.  I said what does that mean?</p>
<p>She looked at me.  She said I guess I should tell you the county coroner of</p>
<p>01:07:20 Haywood County--his name was John Severe [phonetic]--was a doctor.  She said Dr. Severe probably asked them not to do anything to your father because he's your grandmother's half brother.  He was white and of course my grandmother was black.  She said that Dr. Severe is widely respected and they tried to be as accommodating to him as they could.</p>
<p>01:07:53 INTERVIEWER:  When you were a student at Howard and later Washington Square Campus of NYU in the '50s, you recall how you and other students felt about segregation and the lack of civil</p>
<p>01:08:03 rights that most African Americans endured?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Well, I recall that we went to I think it's the Howard Theater in Washington.  You weren't welcome in the other theaters as such, except on a segregated basis.  We were concerned about that.  This was during World War II that I was at Howard.  During wartime, we were</p>
<p>01:08:38  concerned about our good and welfare as students.  Also, why couldn't we go into many of the places, which were still segregated in Washington?  There was much discussion about that among us.  We probably didn't do very much, but periodically a few of us would undertake to go into a restaurant and be denied entrance.  But it never became an issue in the</p>
<p>01:09:11 sense of escalating into arrest at that point in time.  That was a little early.  This was 1943.  From '43 to '45, I was at Howard.</p>
<p>Of course we were also concerned</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0005">0005</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>01:09:25 about our studies.  There were a lot of uniformed young men on the campus as a part of the training program that the federal government had at that point in time.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  You joined the NAACP on the staff in 1953 right before the Brown decision and a little more than a year and a half before Emmett Till was murdered.  Share with us the mood</p>
<p>01:09:51 of the NAACP staff and leadership, and tell us about some of the personalities you met.</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Well, I don't want to give you a wandering answer.  I started work in the fall of 1953 to do a special project for Gloster Current, director of branches in Baltimore, Maryland, which was one of our largest branches in the country.</p>
<p>01:10:15 It also had as its president a Dr. Lily M. Jackson, who was very well known throughout the country because she was very colorful, a very strong and aggressive NAACP leader well</p>
<p>01:10:28 respected in Baltimore, and difficult to please.</p>
<p>Gloster Current at a staff meeting</p>
<p>Introduced me as a temporary field secretary, and that I was going to Baltimore to do a six-week membership campaign for the Baltimore branch.  Thurgood Marshall, who was sitting a couple of seats away from me laughed loudly and said, "Gloster, why are</p>
<p>01:10:58 you doing that to that girl?  You should be ashamed of yourself."</p>
<p>I did not know what that meant until I got to Baltimore and found how demanding and difficult it was to work for Ms. Jackson, but I did.  We had a membership campaign which ran for six weeks.  Her daughter, Juanita Jackson Mitchell, at that time, was a first organizer of the youth program</p>
<p>01:11:27 for the national NAACP.</p>
<p>She worked with me and we survived each other.  I was baptized in that particular branch experience and worked.  At that point, there was a</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0006">0006</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>01:11:47 man who was the president of Parks Sausage, which was an early black corporation which was if not the first of its kind, was one of the first of its kind.  One of the great founders was a locally well-known man whose income supposedly was derived from numbers and that type of thing.  I became very friendly with those men and was able to get them to support</p>
<p>01:12:18 the NAACP.  Those were the extremes.  Ms. Jackson was a great church leader and these men were on the other side of the spectrum.  They came together for the purpose of supporting this common cause.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Would that have been Henry Parks?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Yes, Henry G. Parks.  The man was William Adams.</p>
<p>01:12:38 INTERVIEWER:  Little Willie.</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  He was always very nice to me.  I always felt very comfortable and safe with him and Henry Parks.  I was quite young then.</p>
<p>01:12:48 INTERVIEWER:  Let me take you back to the New York office and the people you met there.  Thurgood Marshall, whom you just mentioned a moment ago, obviously you knew of him because you'd been active in the NAACP as a young girl and in later years.  What were your impressions of him when you met him?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Well, first of all, I had to get accustomed to his</p>
<p>01:13:09 language.  I never heard so many cuss words in my life, which was colorful.  Nobody minded.  He was a wonderful raconteur.  He had a tremendous sense of humor.  I said this is Thurgood Marshall?</p>
<p>He was also very effective in getting you to do things and making difficult subjects sound easy.  He said we'll</p>
<p>01:13:41 be going to Hoxie, Arkansas.  He said you'll be able to do that.  It'll be a good first experience for you to get to know the parents there and the children.  It'll be something that</p>
<p>01:13:54 you'll remember for years to come.  Of course, he was right, but it wasn't pie like he claimed that it would be.  But he was good at getting people to do things and also inspiring them.  He's an exceptionally bright man, but it was all beneath this demeanor of roughness and semi-crudeness.  It's a manner he affected, and he did well</p>
<p>01:14:19 with making you comfortable with him.</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0007">0007</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  What were your impressions of Roy Wilkins?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Very elegant man, one who was extremely similar, concerned about the language and its use, the syntax and sentence structure.  Of course, I learned much about grammar and composition from Roy Wilkins, who wrote beautifully.  He also was a very unpretentious</p>
<p>01:14:47 person.  He did not want any ceremony.  He rode the subway, which at that time was 5 cents going and coming to work.  He did not want bodyguards or attendants.</p>
<p>01:15:00</p>
<p>He was a purist when it came to commitment to the association.  He wanted the staff to dedicate themselves to achieving the goals which were set out for them in terms of their work and to at all times be properly attired and achieve the right demeanor to present the NAACP as a wholesome, serious organization</p>
<p>01:15:29 who had intelligent people as its representatives.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Walter White?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Walter White was colorful.  He enjoyed people.  He embraced people and he enjoyed the social interaction.  He also liked the spotlight.  Wilkins, on the other hand, did not seek the spotlight.  He tolerated it, but Walter White</p>
<p>01:15:58 thrived in the spotlight.  Also, because of his people skills and his ability to interact, he was able to get certain information in terms of doing his research.  He was very</p>
<p>01:16:14 fair.  He would be presumed to be Caucasian, unless you would know otherwise.  He was successful in going into places like Mississippi, Georgia, and Arkansas and investigating lynchings and other incidents, and coming back without having been assaulted or thrown in jail.  He enjoyed that kind of activity and the fact that he could</p>
<p>01:16:41 live in these two worlds.  It was effective.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  A moment ago you mentioned Hoxie, Arkansas, and that took, you into contact with Daisy Bates.  What do you recall about Daisy Bates?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Ms. Bates was a very dedicated civil rights worker, but she also had a sense of style.  She</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0008">0008</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>01:17:03 enjoyed the spotlight as well.  She was not ever shy.  At that time, the governor of Arkansas was Orval Faubus.  He was known to be anti-black, a segregationist, and was</p>
<p>01:17:24 determined to keep the schools in Arkansas separate.  Of course, Daisy Bates on the other hand--this is in the '50s now.  This is just before '56.  This was 1954, when I first went to Little Rock.  Then I went back two or three years after that during this period leading up to the integration of Central High.</p>
<p>Daisy was colorful, aggressive, and</p>
<p>01:17:54 she didn’t mind the spotlight.  She was very talkative.  She too was a people person.  She was able to get branches and what we call the little people and the simple people, many of whom were very literate to follow and come in to the NAACP.  At this point in time, we were focusing on education to get their children, who were students, a better education.</p>
<p>01:18:24 She was able to get many of them to become active in the units in the various cities and towns in Arkansas who had never been active before.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  A moment ago, when you</p>
<p>01:18:38 and I were talking, we mentioned Rosa Parks.  What are your memories of Rosa Parks?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Well, Ms. Parks was a very charming and gracious lady.  I think I said at one point laconic.  She was of few words, but when she spoke, you listened to her.  She was very kind.  In those days, when you traveled as a field secretary as I</p>
<p>01:10:05 was, you would stay in the homes of NAACP people in various parts of the country.  Usually they were officers of the branch.  Once when I first went to Montgomery, I stayed with Ms. Parks.  This is before of course she left Alabama.  She and her husband both were very pleasant and comfortable people.  They were quietly militant.  They weren't</p>
<p>01:19:34 bombastic.  They didn’t make a lot of noise about it.  They just would act.</p>
<p>At that point, she was still secretary of the branch.  She was very determined that we should do</p>
<p>01:19:50 more with our youth.  She was focusing at that time a lot in getting the youth in Montgomery to organize and to take certain steps in terms of preparing them to move forward in the integration movement.</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0009">0009</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Do you remember E.D. Nixon, the president of Montgomery Branch, a Pullman car porter.</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Yes, I do.</p>
<p>01:20:14 INTERVIEWER:  What do you recall about him?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Well, he was a very dedicated person with a strong commitment to civil rights.  He was committed to the NAACP and the way he believed that we had to have an integrated society if we as blacks were to thrive and achieve in this country.  He was one of the few</p>
<p>01:20:40 voices who would withstand a lot of the pressure in Alabama to take a stand.  He refused to give up the membership roles of the NAACP in Alabama when the Attorney General</p>
<p>01:20:56 demanded it.  After that period, you may recall, the NAACP was banned from operating in Alabama.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  You had been at the NAACP about a year and a half when news comes that this boy, Emmett Till, has been found dead in a river in Mississippi.  Do you remember hearing the news about that and what the reaction of the people in the</p>
<p>01:21:20 office here were?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Yes.  I remember.  It was considered in our office to be a great tragedy because just before then--I'm sorry I can't remember the town--one of our branch presidents had been killed in Mississippi.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Gus Counch [phonetic].</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  I think yeah.  We were in the throws of that.  Because the NAACP was encouraging them to</p>
<p>01:21:53 continue the voter education registration campaign, this brought about his death, the branch presidents.  This one child, as he</p>
<p>01:22:07 was presumed to be, was killed.  It was felt at that point that Mississippi was completely going out of bounds, and that nothing was sacred or safe in the state.  The NAACP really had to stay behind its people to help them and to keep them from having to cave in or to become too intimidated to keep the movement going.  If the NAACP didn't continue</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0010">0010</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>01:22:42 to function, then we would not be able to do anything about an Emmett Till.  This was the great concern, whether this would stop the movement.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Do you remember any interaction with Mamie Bradley, Emmett Till's mother?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Yes.  I arranged a tour, I guess, of NAACP branches for Ms. Bradley to visit.  Actually, I</p>
<p>01:23:14 accompanied her for some of the time to some of the cities, which we arranged for her to visit.  She was a woman who was very articulate.  As she campaigned or visited the units</p>
<p>01:23:33 across the country I should say, she grew more militant and more informed, and became more involved.  Then of course she started speaking more forcefully and making demand which should be met in terms of acquisition of civil rights and justice for her son.  She insisted, for example, on opening the casket when he was funeralized in Chicago, which was</p>
<p>01:24:06 quite an experience for one to have to see him lying in the casket and showing the evidences of him having been killed.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Before we began this interview, you and I were talking about Clarence Norris, one of the Scottsboro Boys.  Tell that story once again, how you came to know him.</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Our office moved to</p>
<p>01:24:32 1790 Broadway, off Columbus Circle.  One day this man came into the office and the switchboard operator called me to say we have a man here who needs help, which often that</p>
<p>01:24:45 happened.  At that point I was I think executive assistant to Roy Wilkins or assistant director between Mr. Wilkins and Dr. Marcel [phonetic].  I went out to see this man and it developed his name was Clarence Norris.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Did you recognize him?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Not at first, but then after he started talking I realized</p>
<p>01:25:12 that I had seen his pictures, and that he was one of the Scottsboro Boys.  He said--</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  [Interposing] He was a fugitive, was he not?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Yes, he was.  He had been for several years, so this was not new.  We knew this in the NAACP that he had escaped.</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0011">0011</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  But you didn't know</p>
<p>01:25:30 where he was and didn't know he'd walk into the office, did you?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  I didn't have the faintest idea he was in the New York area.  This had to be I guess in the</p>
<p>01:25:40 late '60s.  He said, "I went to the old office years ago," meaning 20 West 40th Street, "and I met the lady who was the office manager.  He described her.  I said, "Ms. Branch?"  He said yes.  He said, "If she's here, she'll help me."  I said, "You need help?"  He said yes.  I called Bobbie Branch and asked her if I could bring him around to her.  She</p>
<p>01:26:11 said yes.  She remembered him.</p>
<p>Our officer manager then, as you might recall, Bobbie Branch, embraced people.  She was very gregarious.  She welcomed him and said, "I'll help you.  What do you need?"  He needed some money of course.  He said his wife, I believe, that first time--I think his wife was ill.  She said, "Well, let me see if Mr. Wilkins is</p>
<p>01:26:43 here and I'll take you over to meet him."  I told her he wasn't there, but Dr. Marcel was.</p>
<p>He met Dr. Marcel and they talked.  Dr. Marcel was a very thoughtful--</p>
<p>01:26:54 [break in video] --if we had provided some further assistance.  Willie Norris said, "Yes, I need assistance.  I want to clear my name before I die."  That's how this relationship again with him was resumed after the NAACP many, many years ago had been instrumental in helping them until a political problem arose where the communist party became involved and</p>
<p>01:27:28 the NAACP stepped aside.  That was when he was a much younger man, shortly after having been arrested for the rape to begin with.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  He escaped and came to New York City, and now he's coming to the NAACP and making a request for assistance for pardon.  How did that follow through?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Actually, for money it was his first request.  When he</p>
<p>01:27:50 met and talked with John Marcel, Marcel said we want to see how we can provide some meaningful assistance for you, meaning to try to get him</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0012">0012</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>01:28:07 settled into a job and whatever.  He said, "I want to clear my name before I die."  That's really when our general counsel--not that visit--but it was arranged to give him some money and for him to return.  When he returned it was then he talked without general counsel.</p>
<p>Mr. Wilkins had spoken to Nathaniel Jones, who was our general counsel at</p>
<p>01:28:35 that point, and asked if you would join Wilkins when Mr. Norris came back into the office.  From that point on, Nathaniel Jones became the person who was exploring how our legal department could help him.  He assigned one of the bright, young attorneys, whose name was James Meyerson [phonetic], to work on the issue of getting a full pardon for</p>
<p>01:29:04 Willie Norris.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Eventually Meyerson and Wilkins and--</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  [Interposing] Jones.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Jones and Norris go to</p>
<p>01:29:13 Alabama and secure his pardon.</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Meet the governor and the attorney general and get a full pardon from then for Willie.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  That's a wonderful, wonderful story.</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Following that, the book was written, The Last of the Scottsboro Boys.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Many young people</p>
<p>01:29:32 became involved in the NAACP through youth council.  For a time you worked as field secretary and director of education.  What were your goals for the programs that involved young people?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Well, first I should say I was never director of education.  June Shagaloff was.  I was director of a lot of things.  I</p>
<p>01:29:50 can't remember all of the jobs I had.  Every five years I would transfer to a new job.  I was an assistant director to the executive and a director, and then finally director</p>
<p>01:30:07 of operations and director of programs, under which education fell at that point.  I'm sorry; I forgot the other part of the question.</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0013">0013</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  What were the goals that you worked on that involved young people?  What were the programs that you worked on that involved young people?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Well, the programs</p>
<p>01:30:29 which involved young people and which I worked early on were ACT-SO, which is the Academic, Cultural, Scientific  Olympics.  They subsequently added Afro to the title.  That was for the purpose of developing academic excellence and general achievement as far as youth were concerned.  It could be in any of 24 fields--arts and science, and literary--in</p>
<p>01:31:11 general, and the youth were organized on a local level according to the program.</p>
<p>This program was founded by Benjamin Hooks and Vernon Jarrett, who was a</p>
<p>01:31:24 newspaper reporter from Chicago.  Benjamin became the successor to Roy Wilkins.  We organized units across the country such similar to youth units with an advisor for ACT-SO.  The idea was to recruit those who showed promise locally.  They do have local competitions, then regional competitions, then national competitions.  The program is still</p>
<p>01:31:50 going strong today.  There are some 600 ACT-SO units across the country which are actively engaged.  One here in metropolitan New York, where we are at the moment, is the largest one because there are some 17 branches who participate.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  If you count the local branch participation, this is probably the largest African American</p>
<p>01:32:19 talent-based scholarship program in the country.</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Yes, and the most enduring.  Scholarships are given; rewards are given; medals are given</p>
<p>01:32:29 at the national convention.  We have had such people as I was trying to think of some people who have come through the ACT-SO program.  I think there's a young man who was the conductor of a symphony who appears at Lincoln Center, who was an ACT-SO graduate.  We have others.  I don't want to try to name names because I'll leave out some who--</p>
<p>01:32:59 INTERVIEWER:  [Interposing] They're a distinguished group of achievers.</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Yes, absolutely.</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0014">0014</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  A moment ago you talked about Roy Wilkins succeeding Walter White.  Walter White died.</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Yes, he did.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Roy Wilkins was named to succeed him.  Do you remember any discussion whether or not Roy Wilkins</p>
<p>01:33:19 should have succeeded him or was there another candidate?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  No, not at that time.  Walter White died in 1955 suddenly.  He had been ill and on leave.  He had</p>
<p>01:33:39 a leave of absence, Walter White, and  Roy Wilkins had been serving as administrator.  In his absence as executive, he took over the duties of executive secretary.  When Walter White died while on leave, Roy Wilkins--after the funeral of course--at the next board meeting I believe it was, at the spring board meeting, was named his successor.  There had</p>
<p>01:34:09 been some earlier discussions prior to this.  When Walter White had a leave of absence before, he went around the world I believe a few years before that.  There was some discussion then about whether Roy Wilkins would be his successor.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Succeeding Roy Wilkins was Benjamin Hooks.</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Yes.</p>
<p>01:34:30 INTERVIEWER:  Describe him.</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  He was a Baptist minister, and a dramatic Baptist minister.  His oratorical skills were great.  He enjoyed demonstrating as</p>
<p>01:34:45 he spoke.  He inspired our constituents.  Whereas Roy Wilkins was an intellectual-type speaker who would lay the facts out in elegant prose, Mr. Hooks demonstrated his speeches frequently by his physical activities at the podium.  He used shall I say the gospel approach in terms of inspiring our constituents.  He was effective.  He got the kind of</p>
<p>01:35:19 visceral response which people enjoy during the course of speeches.  He could inspire them also not just to respond to him, but to become actively engaged in the work of the NAACP.</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0015">0015</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>He kept our constituents committed in the units across the country.  He tried to travel as much as he could because they are the connection</p>
<p>01:35:43 between the national office and the constituents.  If they aren't actively engaged in the 50 states across the country, then the NAACP's presence is not being brought to the</p>
<p>01:35:55 fore as it should be and to show how forceful it can be.  It is the only organization of its kind which has shall I say 1,700 units in the 50 states for some 500 youth and college units.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Why do you think it is that the NAACP's accomplishments and achievements are not as well known as one would think they'd be?  After</p>
<p>01:36:21 all, the organization's 100 years old plus, and has a remarkable record of achievement and accomplishment.  Yet it doesn't seem to be as well known as one would think it would be.  Why do you think that is?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  I have no idea except that we as a people don't focus on our history and our heritage.  The NAACP was here before most all of us</p>
<p>01:36:50 were here at this point.  As it has achieved many accomplishments, actually, it has affected the order of life for all of us, whatever color we are.  What is more for our</p>
<p>01:37:07 reaching than the interstate travel bill, for example, the desegregation of the public schools or the public accommodations laws where everybody could get access to places?  What happens I believe is we forget our history.</p>
<p>We live in the period and then we take for granted what there is, and do not retain it as an achievement</p>
<p>01:37:36 which had been caused by the hard work of those who came on before us.  We don't really as a people in this country--not just the black people--we don't really focus on our own American history, what has happened at various periods, and the transitions through which we have gone.  We forget.  Then we take for granted this is my right.  It's here</p>
<p>01:38:05 now.  We don't think about how it was in the past.  The NAACP has been actually forgotten a lot of times when it was the only instrument which was able to achieve certain things</p>
<p>01:38:20 which we now enjoy.  I don't have an answer.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  I don't either.  Let me mention some organizations, some of which have come and gone in the span of the NAACP's history.  Give me your impressions of them.  The Southern Christian Leadership Conference.</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0016">0016</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  SCLC?</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  SCLC.</p>
<p>01:38:41 MS. ROXBOROUGH:  My impression?  Well, I think the SCLC was an effective organization in the sense that it brought to the fore in the minds of the public that the religious leaders in this country were engaged in and active in terms of passing the word of our civil rights and providing inspiration and leadership to their congregations throughout the country.</p>
<p>01:39:15 We should be mindful and become engaged in this struggle, and we can do by showing ourselves and lending our voices.  SCLC was flexible because its leaders could go from one</p>
<p>01:39:31 community to the other and call together the religious leaders in a given community to provide a voice for a particular cause and a particular action.  I think it was helpful in that respect in terms of setting before us actively through the pulpits what it was we needed to do and what we must do.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  What about the Student</p>
<p>01:39:57 Nonviolent Coordinating Committee, my old organization, SNCC?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Yes.  Well you know more about that than I do.  I certainly think that the sit-ins were extraordinary in the sense that they opened the eyes of the old folks, the adults in the country.  This I can do also, the simple act of walking into a café or a 10-cent store as they had</p>
<p>01:40:23 then, lunch counter and sitting there and saying I'm not going to move.  That's something all of us could do.  The students demonstrated that this is something that had not been done,</p>
<p>01:40:35 and that we're going to do it.  They did and it was impressive.  It inspired us as older people to really go out and demonstrate.  If our youth can do it, our children can do it, then why won't we do it?</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  What about the Congress of Racial Equality, CORE?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  CORE was a little more intellectual.  It had an excellent</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0017">0017</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>01:40:57 leader in James Farmer, who formally worked for the NAACP as our program director.  Many of these leaders by the way of the other organizations had gotten their grounding and their foundations in the NAACP, such as Martin Luther King, Jr. did.  His father had been active in the NAACP before him.  The CORE was more integrated than the other groups were</p>
<p>01:41:28 in terms of racial integration.  It appealed to a younger group in general, students and young adults, and they were concerned about demonstrating in black and white the</p>
<p>01:41:48 acquisition of the goals they wanted to achieve.  They had certainly an impact--I believe CORE did--in terms of encouraging non-blacks to participate actively in the civil rights movement.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  What about the Black Panther Party?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Well, the Black Panther Party I believe had the</p>
<p>01:42:10 energy and the ambition, and a sense in my judgment of misdirection eventually.  It started as a militant group wanting to use its power and apply it actively.  Then it veered towards separation and separatism.  Black power became an instrument, in my judgment, to shall I say encourage and focus on black separatism, which I believe and am convinced was then</p>
<p>01:42:47 self-defeating and would be today.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Back to the NAACP for a moment, I think many people think of the NAACP primarily as a legal organization.  It's an organization</p>
<p>01:42:59 that achieved change through legal means through the courts.  Do you think this fairly characterizes the NAACP?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  No.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Why not?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Well, one of the first executive orders that President Roosevelt--not one of the first ones, but an executive order that President</p>
<p>01:43:22 Roosevelt issued about the arms services, the preliminary one, was done as a result of the NAACP's lobbying and campaigning and the fact that Ms. Roosevelt was on our board of directors.  Walter White and Ms. Roosevelt had a good relationship, and it was possible to get Ms. Roosevelt to work with Walter White and Phillip Randolph, and to get</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0018">0018</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>01:43:54 President Roosevelt to understand that an executive order desegregating federal installations should be issued.  Of course that wasn't integration, but it was a first step.</p>
<p>01:44:12 That was done without any legal action.</p>
<p>The first civil rights law was achieved primarily through lobbying and under the aegis of Clarence Mitchell, the Washington Bureau.  Again, that historic was passed by congress as a result of lobbying.  It was within the confines of reality, but it wasn't an illegal act.  I</p>
<p>01:44:40 think the public accommodations are a lot of the same things.  There are so many things which widely affect our society, which the NAACP inspired, led and accomplished, which were not legal actions; such actions as far as litigation is concerned.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Again, this may be redundant.  Why is it that many people think of the NAACP as</p>
<p>01:45:06 primarily a legal organization and these other activities that you've mentioned aren't associated in the public mind with the NAACP?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  I suspect one of the</p>
<p>01:45:15 reasons is our lawyers appeared before the Supreme Court so many times.  Former general counsel Robert Carter had made some 36 appearances before the Supreme Court and won about 30 of those cases.  Before that, Thurgood Marshall, before he became a justice when he was NAACP counsel, appeared before the Supreme Court.  I can't remember the exact</p>
<p>01:45:45 number now, but it was more than two dozen times and of course most of those cases were won.  This of course, the publicity of these cases, set in the minds of people that legal action is responsible for our progress in this country, and to an important extent it is.  Without the grass roots lobbying and without the meticulous work of putting before our</p>
<p>01:46:22 congressman both on local, state, and federal levels the need to enact certain laws and the pressure from the grass roots, we would not be where we are today.</p>
<p>01:46:36 INTERVIEWER:  Skipping to another personality, do you think Malcolm X had any effect during his life on the NAACP or civil rights generally speaking?  Did his death or his murder have an impact on the NAACP, particularly in northern cities, northern communities?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Well, this is one person's opinion.  I think certainly</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0019">0019</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>01:47:04 he demonstrated the fact that discipline could be achieved in leadership.  He exercised discipline in the sense of the followers who became committed to the movement which he lead believed and committed themselves to conforming the guidelines and expectations.  These were in so many instances young men who had been street people, who had</p>
<p>01:47:40 no commitment as such except to survive the best way they could for themselves.  They became part of a cohesive group, interacting with each other, and willing to help each</p>
<p>01:47:52 other, and then project this on to the community.  I think that's one excellent cause he served.</p>
<p>I believe that his death did have a serious impact because of the fact that it represented the death of a leader who had a following over whom he had shall I say such vast experience that they could be effectively banned together to</p>
<p>01:48:27 achieve progress by folks who have been formally on the streets and who have formally not been engaged in any meaningful activity.  This was important example it seems to me for those of us in civil rights, not that we agree with all of his philosophy.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Do you think you could feel a measurable impact that he had, particularly after his death, that</p>
<p>01:48:56 there were people within the NAACP perhaps who said perhaps in some ways we should emulate his dedication, his conviction?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  I think there were</p>
<p>01:49:08 some people like that.  Measurably there were, especially among our youth.  They felt that he had the right idea in terms of his discipline and his rhetoric, which became more bland before he died than it was when he began when he was preaching almost anarchy at one point in time.  He modified his position to develop pressure on what he called the power</p>
<p>01:49:44 structure by threatening and also showing that he represented a force n the community--in the society I should say, not just the community.</p>
<p>I think this impressed especially our younger adults and youth in the NAACP.  You had a reaction that they believed that he was on the right track or he's a good example for us to follow.</p>
<p>01:50:16 INTERVIEWER:  You were married to an attorney who worked with the NAACP to effect change.  How did his work construct your lives together?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Well, before I knew</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0020">0020</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>01:50:28 him, John, he was Chairman of the Legal and Redress Committee of Detroit Branch, having been born in Michigan and reared in Michigan.  When I first went to Detroit to work with the NAACP branch there and Arthur Johnson as executive secretary, we were organizing the first Freedom Fund and Life Membership dinner.</p>
<p>01:50:56 At that point, the Legal and Redress Committee of the Detroit Branch was very active, and they had won two or three cases in Michigan before the Michigan Supreme Court involving housing and education.  John was the lead lawyer in those particular cases.  It was after then that I got to know him.  I always felt that the Detroit Branch was an excellent</p>
<p>01:51:30 example of the kind of activities and accomplishments that an NAACP branch should undertake.</p>
<p>Of course, the work of the legal committee actually got commendations</p>
<p>01:51:46 from the national office and Thurgood Marshall, who was then our general counsel.  That kind of thing impressed me about the importance of having a varied scope of activity in the civil rights movement.  Of course, he on the other hand was supportive of the Detroit Branch's other activities.  We were, shall I say, compatible in the sense, and we</p>
<p>01:52:12 share an interest in terms of civil rights.  That wasn't the reason we married, but that was one of the reasons of the common interest in the early days.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Thinking about the Detroit Branch from your perspective and what you've seen over the years, what is it that makes branch A effective, efficient, hard-fighting</p>
<p>01:52:34 and so on; and branch B lackluster, sleepy, do-nothing?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Its leadership.  I believe it's the leadership.  The extent which your leadership</p>
<p>01:52:45 inspires, the board, and the members will be the extent to which they respond and become creative and are inspired to become creative and do things in a more positive and forceful nature.  I think the key is in the kind of leadership branches have across the country.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Let me ask you to talk about some occasions in the past over</p>
<p>01:53:12 time when the leadership of the NAACP has faced real challenges or difficult circumstances.  I'm thinking about the barring of the NAACP in Alabama, the lawsuit against the NAACP in Mississippi because of the boycott.  Let's talk about those things.  How did the people here respond to that?</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0021">0021</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  When you say here, are you talking--</p>
<p>01:53:34</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  [Interposing] I mean New York, in the New York Office.</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  About the national office.</p>
<p>01:53:37 INTERVIEWER:  National office.</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  First of all, they were defiant, one.  We are not going to give those membership lists up.  That was the first thing.  Second, we've got to find a way to work around this and continue our work.  We had employed recently Ms. Ruby Hurley [phonetic] who was sent to Alabama to organize units of the</p>
<p>01:54:05 NAACP in the southeast region, which is the confederate states.  Ms. Hurley had been in Alabama not too long--I guess probably less than a year--doing this and organizing units headquartered in Birmingham, as I recall.</p>
<p>She moved after the NAACP was banned.  The office there was moved to Atlanta, but as a result of that, she</p>
<p>01:54:36 and some other NAACP volunteer workers would visit these states in which the NAACP had been banned, Alabama and I forget the other state.  There were two states whose</p>
<p>01:54:59 membership roles were taken, would not be given up I should say.  In any case, the thing I wanted to say is Ms. Hurley and other volunteers went almost surreptitiously into communities to work, again, memberships with the NAACP and to organize certain things like getting petitions signed and to get them to get organized to go to the polls to</p>
<p>01:55:32 register, go to the courthouse or wherever to register and vote.</p>
<p>It was done under the cover of night so to speak without the banner of the NAACP in the daytime having these meetings.  It made it shall I say dangerous.  Ms. Hurley was threatened many times.  Her life was threatened and she was in danger doing this, but she was a</p>
<p>01:55:56 spokesperson who was able to get these groups in these various states in Alabama and Georgia and Mississippi to come together to agree to do certain things in terms of</p>
<p>01:56:09 continuing the fight for civil rights in their communities.</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0022">0022</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  What about when the local leadership would be under attack, as in the case of Medgar Evers assassination?  What was the New York Headquarters' response?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Well, its response was to send people into Mississippi to fill the void; actually, to reassure</p>
<p>01:56:30 the people that the NAACP was continuing its fight with Medgar's death.  This was just even more important that we demonstrate that we were not intimidated by the fact that he was killed.</p>
<p>Actually, his brother took over the position of field director for the State of Mississippi and he's still there in Mississippi.  He eventually</p>
<p>01:56:57 became Mayor of Philadelphia I believe it was, Charles.  This is the kind of thing the NAACP was forced to do in order to make sure its constituents had examples of our</p>
<p>01:57:14 continuing the work of the association one way or the other.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  What was Medgar Evers like?  You surely knew him.</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Yes, I worked with Medgar.  I was sent to Mississippi in the '60s to interview farmers who had been denied credit, who were subjected to economic reprisals because of their NAACP activities,</p>
<p>01:57:41 continuing to go to the polls to register and vote.</p>
<p>Medgar and I, as a field director, he would drive to the various places because that's the best way to get there.  We went into the Delta area to interview the farmers so I could take these reports back to New York to see how we could help them to survive the winter.  Being denied</p>
<p>01:58:08 credit over the winter season, it meant they had no means of getting food because that was the tradition.  You get credit for the next four months, and then when the spring came</p>
<p>01:58:20 you were able to start planting and you would be able to start paying the bills again.  All of that credit was cut off.</p>
<p>We traveled.  I guess we spent at that point about two weeks doing this.  One particularly difficult time when our farmers were being economic reprisals, we had had two branch presidents who had been killed</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0023">0023</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>01:58:52 just before this particular time.  It was difficult to believe that these people would continue to carry on like this because the situation was so oppressive in Mississippi.  We were driving one night and I had taken off my shoes and felt something on the floor which was cold.  I said to Medgar, "What is this?  Maybe I can move it."  He said, "Well, that's</p>
<p>01:59:22 my shotgun you have your feet on."  Of course my feet flew up.  But this is just to give you an idea of the sense of the environment.</p>
<p>We would drive each night from</p>
<p>01:59:35 wherever we went, Yazoo or whatever town, into which we'd gone at night again--not to further endanger the farmers and the people who were being subjected to these reprisals--and drive back to Mound Bayou, which is a black town in that area, in which there was a motel.  We would go back to stay at that motel and then start out the next day, planning to arrive</p>
<p>02:00:03 in sort of the evening to visit the farmers.  This is the way in which you had to function in those days out of Jackson where you walked around in the daytime and did your interviews.  Does that answer the question?</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Yes, it does.</p>
<p>MALE VOICE:  Pardon me before you move on to the next one.  It's been an hour, so I need to start a new</p>
<p>02:00:26 tape.  Do either of you want a glass of water or anything?  Can we get something for you?</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  No, but I could go to the bathroom.  What a memory.  I</p>
<p>02:00:39 don't remember what I did yesterday.</p>
<p>[END AFC2010039_CRHP0002_MV1.WMV]</p>
<p>[START AFC2010039_CRHP0002_MV2.WMV]</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  --them on first meeting?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Well, I really met them at first at a meeting.  Ms. Bates would plan to have them gather not necessarily an NAACP meeting as such, but just to meet with them, to</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0024">0024</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>01:00:23 talk with them, and I would say to inspire them and to sort of inject discipline.  To keep them together in other words.  They were individual personalities.  I did not get to know them well.  I only knew them as a group in the course of the meetings because they were carefully tended in the sense of for their own security.  This was year before the Central High</p>
<p>01:00:59 School began, the actual process of integration.  I forget the year, but it was '55 or '56.  Then they actually entered the next year in the fall.</p>
<p>01:01:18 The thing that impressed me was the quiet determination of Ernest Green--I remembered him--who later became a member of the NAACP Board of Directors.  Another one whom I remember is Minnie Jean Brown, who had a special assertive personality.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Yes, she did.</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Some of them were quiet.  Others, they were sort of</p>
<p>01:01:45 followers in this sense.  I'm sure they had their own individual personalities outside of the group, but those are the ones I remember most particularly as being responsive and actively ready to go forward with the process of going to school.</p>
<p>The others, I wouldn't say they were followers, I would just say they were engaged in a quieter fashion.  They</p>
<p>01:02:20 were less vociferous or less active in the process, except that they wanted to finish their schooling.  They all had that.</p>
<p>MALE VOICE:  Hold on, one moment.</p>
<p>01:02:35 Okay, we can continue.  Thank you.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Let me ask you about two women from South Carolina whom you may have met, Septima Clark and Bernice Robinson.  They're cousins I believe.</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  I met them, but I didn't really know them, except by reputation that they were very active and engaged.  But I really didn't</p>
<p>01:02:59 know them.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  What about Ella Baker, who worked at the NAACP?</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0025">0025</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Yes.  After she worked for the NAACP is when I met her because she was a very forceful personality.  She became focused on our youth if you recall and actually was involved in the founding of the Student Nonviolent Coordinating</p>
<p>01:03:22 Committee.  She worked in our Department of Branches before I came on board to the NAACP.  She spent considerable time traveling around the country organizing branches,</p>
<p>01:03:33 eliciting memberships, developing membership campaigns, and instructing our branches how to do that.  She was a very forceful woman.  I was always impressed by her determination and her aggressiveness.</p>
<p>At the time when I first started to work for the NAACP, you didn't have that many women who were working in levels up beyond the support levels</p>
<p>01:04:06 in the work arena, period--in other organizations as well.  Most of the females were assistants or secretaries or that type of thing in the NAACP.  For example, Lucille Black who came in at age 17 as a secretary, she worked her way to become membership secretary it was called then of the NAACP.  Bobbie Branch came in as a clerk wound up as</p>
<p>01:04:37 office manager.  Obviously, in NAACP in the legal department, there were always one or two females.  Then when I came on board, one of the few female executives was June Shagaloff,</p>
<p>01:04:55 who was a field director in education, who traveled and worked providing information and support for the legal department and our legal programs.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Not a woman, but Jack Greenberg.  What do you remember about Jack Greenberg?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Well, he was a young lawyer.  He was on board about a year</p>
<p>01:05:18 before I came on.  I got to know him quite well.  Very active.  We were contemporaries in terms of age also.  We were about the same age.  He worked well with Thurgood Marshall.  I believe they were called either associate or assistant counsels during that period, the young lawyers who were brought in.</p>
<p>He was focusing a lot on the</p>
<p>01:05:48 education cases.  That was one of the things that Jack focused on during the period when they were putting together cases in the various communities--about six or eight</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0026">0026</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>01:06:00 communities primarily in the south or as far west as Kansas, which eventually became the group of cases led by Brown to go up through the process on to the Supreme Court.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  What about Robert Carter?  What do you remember of him in those days?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Yes.  Well, Bob was the associate I guess.  He was a</p>
<p>01:06:27 second attorney to Thurgood, who was still NAACP counsel at this point when I came on board and remained so for the next few years.  Bob was the quieter one, but he also was the one who reached out in the communities and spent a lot of time and effort putting together the South Carolina cases, for example.  He eventually pled in a couple of instances during</p>
<p>01:07:05 those trials before the Supreme Court.</p>
<p>He has as wonderful time.  He was meticulous and concerned about amassing the information in an</p>
<p>01:07:18 orderly way.  He spent a lot of times questioning and really you got the feeling that he was being too meticulously difficult, but it wasn't at all.  He had this commitment to make sure that nothing was left unturned and no I was undotted.  As a result, it became sort of laborious sometimes, the work for the people that were working for him; that is,</p>
<p>01:07:47 the assistants and the researchers.  In the final analysis it was what had to be done.  It was not easy, but he was willing to put himself into the task of getting this part of the work done.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Do you want to stop that?  Can you hear the talking down there?</p>
<p>MALE VOICE:  Yeah, I can hear it.</p>
<p>01:08:10 [break in video]</p>
<p>MALE VOICE:  Cameras rolling.  Ready?</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  A moment ago, you mentioned that when you began working here at the NAACP the employment sort</p>
<p>01:08:23 of paralleled what we saw in the larger society.  That is, women in clerical roles and men in the executive roles.  Over time I guess that's changed, but it also strikes me that it contrasts with a different picture in the branch system.  In the branch system, women are presidents.  Women do serve in roles that maybe they weren't expected to serve in.</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0027">0027</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>01:08:45 How has the situation changed over time?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  You mean in terms of the--</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  [Interposing] Of women in the NAACP.</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Well, actually when you think about women's contributions to the NAACP, without the women we wouldn't have an NAACP.  The person</p>
<p>01:09:03 who was responsible for generating the organizing meeting was a woman.  Of course, ever since then we've had women in key roles--not in the majority, but in the very key roles</p>
<p>01:09:19 which were responsible for the evolution of the NAACP.</p>
<p>I think in terms of people like Daisy Lampkin, who was a member of our national board from Pittsburgh; she traveled around the country garnering memberships and helping to organize branches.  That was back in the '30s and '40s before it became fashionable or popular for women to travel.  You</p>
<p>01:09:52 have women who subsequently held positions in the NAACP nationally as program directors and as leaders of various divisions.  For example, Althea Simmons actually succeeded Clarence Mitchell as head of the Washington Bureau.  We had Constance Baker Motley in the legal department who eventually moved up to the leadership role in the NAACP Legal</p>
<p>01:10:28 Defense Fund subsequently.</p>
<p>Women had no defined place in the organization and Ms. Frances Hooks, the wife of Benjamin Hooks, founded when WIN, Women in the NAACP, which</p>
<p>01:10:45 gave them a structure in which to function and reach out and do the things in the NAACP that they had been doing, but in an organized and recognizable fashion.  You wound up having Margaret Bush Wilson become the second female to be Chairman of the Board of the NAACP.  Then the vice chair has developed Roslyn Brock, who has succeeded you as</p>
<p>01:11:14 chair.</p>
<p>As a matter of fact, I don't know if you know this in your research of the NAACP, but the 19 march in New York here in protest to lynching, the silent march, the research in Arkansas of the lynchings and then on to Georgia was done by a female.  She brought the report back for Dr. Dubois, who was involved at that</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0028">0028</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>01:11:52 point in terms of amassing the information, which was the basis on which that march was constructed and held as a result of that report she brought back in 1918.  The march</p>
<p>01:12:10 subsequently was held in 1919 after the information on the lynching and the murders that she had investigated was submitted really through our Washington Bureau to the federal government.  It was felt that nothing would be done, so this march evolved.  Of course Dr. Du Bois was given the greater publicity for having been the leader.  Actually, the responsibility</p>
<p>01:12:40 of putting that together and causing it to happen was the report done by a female.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Did you have any interaction with Dr. Du Bois?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  No, no.  He was even before my time.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  I mean do you ever run into him?  You both live in New York.  I know it's a big city.</p>
<p>01:12:57 MS. ROXBOROUGH:  I met him and had written him for a copy of one of his documents, one of his papers.  He wrote back saying he'd be delighted to send it, to send $5.  I sent the</p>
<p>01:13:13 $5 and got the paper.  He was interesting I gather from those who knew him in our office.  They would relate stories about Dr. Du Bois and how acerbic he could be.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Can you share a story?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Well, I don't remember them well enough to tell, so I won't undertake to do that and mislead the history.</p>
<p>01:13:40 INTERVIEWER:  What would you like the public to know about the work you've done here at the NAACP?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Well, not really.  I never thought about the public knowing much about what I do.  My concern as far as my being a part of the NAACP was to do what I could in my small way to make it through its leaders and that's my satisfaction.</p>
<p>01:14:05 INTERVIEWER:  I'm sure your parents told you don't hide your light under a bushel.</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  They sure did.</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0029">0029</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>01:14:08 INTERVIEWER:  There must be something here that you've done here that you are proud of among other things.  Among all the things you've done here, there must be things that stand out, something that you're happy that you did.</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  I'd have to give some thought to that.  I can't…  I've had to do a lot of different things over the years.  I wound up getting into that position where it was felt</p>
<p>01:14:36 that I was flexible and I could fit into a lot of different places doing a lot of different jobs.</p>
<p>The reason I'm still probably at the NAACP in one sense--I worked as a full-time person until 1997--was every five years I moved into a different department or different job.  I have held, let's see,</p>
<p>01:15:00 probably about 8 or 10 jobs in almost every department in the association except its accounting department.  I can't count.</p>
<p>The satisfaction I got was learning</p>
<p>01:15:17 how the NAACP functions and how I could make it more effectively function in that particular area.  For example, I went from the branch department as an assistant to Gloster Current and a field secretary at large.  Now that was my baptism.  If you traveled in the early '50s, and as a female, a young, unattached--I wasn't married then female--it was</p>
<p>01:15:38 quite an experience.  First, you had to be sure in the cities where you went and the meetings and whatever, that you were properly on your guard in terms of the male-female interaction.  Then you had to be concerned about the branch president who was an authority, but you were a young female.  You had that as a thing, traveling in those days.  It's</p>
<p>01:16:06 no issue in later years, but it was unusual apparently for young, unattached women to travel into the kinds of byways I traveled.</p>
<p>That was an education.  I thank the</p>
<p>01:16:21 NAACP for educating me, giving me the experience of being educated.  Each time you had to be careful.  You had to learn diplomacy.  You had to learn self-protection, and you had to do your job.  Now all of that was combined in the process when I started work for the NAACP.  I won't go into all the departments, but I've worked in virtually every department.</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0030">0030</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>01:16:46 For me, it was always a good female when they said to me, "Well, you've done the basic organizing in the membership department.  We need you as an executive assistant to the executive secretary.  We would like to get you to move into the executive department.  So I did.  I was director of operations at one point, director of programs, and I wound up</p>
<p>01:17:20 being development director.</p>
<p>With the education I got at the NAACP and the knowledge, I could use that for marketing.  Then I of course wound up going to school taking</p>
<p>01:17:35 courses so that I would know the technical side of fundraising.  Then you had to learn how to respect confidences.  I've learned an awful lot about the leaders of the association, the executive directors primarily; and what makes them tick and how they do this, that, and the other, or what they shouldn't do, what they did do, and shouldn't</p>
<p>01:17:59 happen, whatever.  It was a part of the education in terms of understanding what the NAACP needed and what they needed is leaders.</p>
<p>It's hard for me to say to you I'm most proud of this or that or the other.  There's probably something I am most proud of.  But I guess I'm proud that we were able to keep the parents inspired in Hoxie, to keep</p>
<p>01:18:25 the children, walking the children to school every day, and getting them.  That school board voluntarily desegregated its schools, but the parents needed support and help.  I</p>
<p>01:18:37 got a sense of satisfaction of walking with these children, holding their hands, going to school with them.  Then they are persevering so that they wound up not being forced out of the school.</p>
<p>It's hard for me to pick an item like an accomplishment.  I don't know what accomplishment I might have achieved that would be worth talking about in</p>
<p>01:18:59 the sense of an event.  It would be cumulative the fact that I've been able to serve.  I'm not answering your question, I know.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  It's okay.  Let me ask one more.  In Hoxie and in other places where you went traveling for the NAACP, were there times where you felt in fear of your life?</p>
<p>MS. ROXBOROUGH:  Afterwards, yes.  A</p>
<p>01:19:20 funny thing about it is when you're in danger--like Medgar and I were traveling around and I didn't realize I had my feet on the shotgun there--and being intimidated and going</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0031">0031</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>01:19:32 across cotton fields and other fields at night to get to a local meeting which was being held, and the fact that there were police patrolling in the Delta area, my reaction of fear has come after I've gotten through it.  Because you don't have time to be afraid.  I have found that after I said you're stupid.  How could you get into such as situation out in the</p>
<p>01:20:03 middle of nowhere and nobody on whom to call.  But the fear comes as far as I can recall after you've gotten out of that particular physical situation.  It does come, but later.  I think if you're pushed to do something or have to do it, you're more focused on "How can I get this done?"  That's just been my experience.</p>
<p>01:20:30 My parents always had said to me you're an idiot if you get afraid while you're doing something because you're becoming your own worst enemy, and you act without logic or reason.</p>
<p>01:20:43 You don't want to do that.  You want to plan and try to do what is the most appropriate to safeguard yourself and reach that goal, whatever it is.  Some things I look at now.  As I said, some of the travels in the ‘50s, say I spent a summer in Arkansas traveling to the various branches--El Dorado, Arkansas and Cotton Plant, Arkansas, I never</p>
<p>01:21:15 heard of it until I went there--and places where the white citizens in the town, the power structure, the worst thing that they could learn was that a visitor for the NAACP branch from New York was coming in to stir up trouble.  That was the kind of environment in which I worked, so many instances, during that five-year period that I served as a field</p>
<p>01:21:53 secretary.</p>
<p>I guess I must've worked in about 40 states.  Some of them, the western north, were not as intimidating as the south, but I traveled frequently</p>
<p>01:22:06 in Mississippi, also in Georgia, also Alabama.  Those states were where the tensions were greatest and the people were most fearful, including the local units were exceedingly careful.  That was a learning experience for me about people and how you could survive and accommodate yourself to staying in their homes and feeling that you were bringing them danger,</p>
<p>01:22:40 the fact that I was there sleeping in their room.  There was nothing secret eventually.  The town knows what the folks are doing.</p>
<p>Those experiences have I think made me maybe more humane today and made me understand that people are imperfect, but they are worth any help you can give to ameliorate the problems and negative problems.  I</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0032">0032</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>01:23:17 think the NAACP has had that kind of an effect in communities where it has functioned as an entity.  People have felt that they could get help going to the NAACP, that there would be</p>
<p>01:23:33 something done in their behalf.  I think they believed that.  I believe in large measure they still do.  We, on the other hand, should be accountable and responsible and our leadership should be effective in the sense that they should be able to reach out to people and inspire their confidence about what they do as an example.  Any help you can give to</p>
<p>01:24:01 make that happen should be given.  I still haven't answered your question, have I?</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  That's okay.  Thank you for giving your help.  Thank you.  I think we're through.</p>
<p>[END AFC2010039_CRHP0002_MV2.WMV]</p>
<p></p>
<p>Irvine,  CA Ubiqus Reporting, Inc. New York, NY</p>
<p>(949)  477 4972  (212) 227 7440</p>
<p>www.ubiqus.com</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</tei2>


