<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!--<DOCTYPE tei2 SYSTEM "/itssgml/sgmlstd/dtds/ammem2/ammem2_xml.dtd"> -->
<!--
<!DOCTYPE tei2
  SYSTEM "/itssgml/sgmlstd/dtds/ammem2/ammem2axml_noURLs.dtd"
[<!ENTITY % images SYSTEM "BLA BLA BLA">
%images;]>
-->


<tei2>
   <teiheader type="text" creator="Manuscript Division, Library of Congress" status="new" date.created="02/01/2006">
   </teiheader>
   <text type="manuscript">
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0001">0001</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
      <body>
         <div>

<p>NATIONAL MUSEUM OF AFRICAN AMERICAN HISTORY AND CULTURE</p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p>Civil Rights History Project</p>
<p></p>
<p>Smithsonian Institute's National Museum of African American History &amp; Culture and the Library of Congress, 2011</p>
<p></p>
<p>Robert L. Carter oral history interview</p>
<p></p>
<p>conducted by Patricia Sullivan</p>
<p></p>
<p>in New York, New York, Oct. 23, 2010</p>
<p></p>
<p>[START afc2010039_crhp0001_mv1]</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Say your name, where</p>
<p>00:00:12 were you born, when.</p>
<p>JUDGE ROBERT LEE CARTER:  I was born in Caryville, Florida.  My name is Robert, middle initial L for Lee and Carter.  I think the name Robert is a name that's common, I don't think I have to spell that.  Lee is L-E-E and Carter is a common name, that's spelled C-A-R-T-E-R.  So I think I have a common name that’s not</p>
<p>00:00:55 unusual.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER 2:  Wonderful.  Okay.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  I was not, I hope, named after the confederate general Robert Lee but I may have been at the time because I came from the South and during that period the southern generals and stuff like that were considered heroic by black people.  But I don't know.</p>
<p>00:02:08 INTERVIEWER:  Judge Carter, you're a</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0002">0002</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>child of the Great Migration, tell us about where and when you born and how you came to come North.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  I was born in</p>
<p>00:02:20 Caryville, Florida.  And when I was very young, after my mother birthed me, I was part of migration of family out of the South to the North in the Great Migration.  My family was born free, we were—I think maybe it was 60 years after the Civil War and so we were a free black coming out of the South in the Great Migration.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  And what year was that?</p>
<p>00:03:20 JUDGE CARTER:  What?</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  What year were you born?</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  I was born in 1917.  In Caryville I said earlier, in Caryville, Florida.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  And where did your family move to?  Your father was already up north.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  My father has—my</p>
<p>00:03:47 mother was in Florida birthing me and I think that he was or they were part of the agricultural family but because of the war he apparently had some charisma or was a man who was</p>
<p>00:04:22 just not peon because he has some intelligence.  They sent him north and he was working in a factory and after my mother birthed me she joined him and the rest of the family in Newark.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Newark, okay.  What are you earliest memories about growing up in Newark?</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  My father died when I</p>
<p>00:05:03 was a year old and my mother had no special education, she was not an ignorant woman she had had some schooling but she did not have enough schooling to get a job other than washing clothes for white people.  And as she did to keep bread on the table for us.  And I lived with her by present standards in poverty until I was 12.  When I was 12 years old my</p>
<p>00:06:05 oldest sister married, she was a woman who sewed and made clothes.  And she married this man who owned a bar in Linden, New Jersey.  And that was sort of like a thing coming out</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0003">0003</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>00:06:41 of poverty.  She insisted that he remained—that all the family lived together and so she lived with him.  And the family all together enabled us to get better housing and every time we sort of moved it was to improve our living conditions.  After I was 12 years old I became for the first time, with her marriage, I was able to have a bathroom for myself,</p>
<p>00:07:29 an indoor and an indoor bath.  Until that time I had to use outhouses with other people, I remember that with such distaste.  And fortunately it was sort of—her marrying this man was sort of like the period when—you know in a white fairytale when this poor girl marries this rich man and it was similar to that because it opened the doors for me to mainstream</p>
<p>00:08:25 prerogative, I had never been in indoor toilets and stuff like that.  All of what I learned about the difference between the poor and the rich, for example, is that poor</p>
<p>00:08:55 people never or rarely learn what they need to know, they live—middle class people can live on the streets and stuff like that.  But when it comes time to—if they need to know something, they know where to get it.  And second thing was when the poor I remember is that the poor people act out their life on the streets, middle class people do the same thing but</p>
<p>00:09:47 behind doors.  And they have porches and stuff and they do not have to live their life on the street.  I saw when I was on Boyden which was once one of the worst slums in the ghetto and it has been rehabilitated or what do you call it, it's now—the city of Newark has redone Boyden Street, it was one of the worst slums and they  rejuvenated or whatever that you call</p>
<p>00:10:49 they're doing.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Well education, you wrote in your memoir that your desire for education early on inspired you.  I mean schooling and education, what</p>
<p>00:11:08 opened you up to that in the way that you went ahead and succeeded so well?</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Well I was not skillful with my hands and I knew that somehow I was going to find a way into the mainstream and get an education and find my way there.  And what I recognized was the only way I could do that was to get an education.  I was considered smart</p>
<p>00:12:01 and I skipped in school and stuff like that.  And that was an advantage to me and also I read a lot, undisciplined reading but at the same time it exposed me to a lot of ideas and stuff.  And I knew somehow I had to be in the mainstream, find my way to the mainstream or else I would not survive.  And so I recognized that and I spent a lot of time in the</p>
<p>00:12:52 library at a public library close by.  Unfortunately my reading was undisciplined, I liked to read novels and history, historic novels and stuff.  And from time to time some</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0004">0004</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>00:13:22 real hard disciplined reading I would do.  But for the most part it was not the kind of hardnosed reading that forms a brilliant mind.  But anyway any kind of reading helps.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  It helps.  What were schools like in Newark and then in East Orange?</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  What what?</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  What were the schools</p>
<p>00:13:52 like?</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  There was Newark High.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Were they integrated?</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  No.  When I was in Newark until I was 12 years old, that's when we were in poverty and the people from the South, the migrations from the South was from—my sisters were at the age of puberty and my mother was very worried that</p>
<p>00:14:34 they would—that the guys would ask them and that they would be impregnated early on and she wanted desperately to get out of there.  And when my sister Mammie [phonetic]</p>
<p>00:14:50 married this guy had this bar and grill, she was able to satisfy that because the guys would be on the street after my sisters who at that time who were, you know, 16 and so and she was certain that they might be impregnated and stuff and she was very worried about that.  And that of course showed a double standard because I had more freedom.  She was</p>
<p>00:15:38 not worried about me impregnating anybody which she should have been that concerned but she was not.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  When did you become aware of race?</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  I think early on when I was in maybe the sixth grade or so,  we had two girls in the class were friends, a black girl and a white girl.  And I remember this to this</p>
<p>00:16:30 day, the white girl had bangs and you know she was—with her hair back, the black girl had braids and she wouldn't tie her hair back but she tried to.  They were very close</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0005">0005</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>00:16:51 friends.  And at one point the black girl and the white girl had an argument and the white girl went to her teacher and complained.  And the teacher had no sympathy for her, she told her you should stay with your own kind.  And that showed me how prejudice affected ourselves.  But this was in the Newark school and even though this teacher said that to</p>
<p>00:17:38 this white girl, had no sympathy for her, in Newark the school they sort of stayed back and allowed things to play out.  Well when I was in East Orange school they were adverse to any black/white intercourse, they didn't like that at all and they intervened.  And what that showed me is that the very faces of prejudice, I'm sure that my teachers in East</p>
<p>00:18:22 Orange, now in Newark were as concerned about - - maybe as prejudice as the teachers in East Orange were proved to be.  But they sit back and let things play out.</p>
<p>00:18:44 And so what that showed me is how white prejudice has various forms.  The East Orange people intervened and wanted segregation to be imposed, they couldn't do it by law anymore but they wanted it imposed.  The other people, the teachers in Newark, were not that—they was concerned I guess but they didn't interfere.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  You had very different</p>
<p>00:19:30 experience, you write about in your book, at Barrington High School where you went for two years and then you to East Orange High School in your third year of high school.  Could you talk about—I think a good example that you write about, what happened around the swimming pool, how it was organized, how it changed and what your role was in that.</p>
<p>00:19:51 JUDGE CARTER:  Well I don't know—I don't remember what grade I was in now.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  It doesn't matter.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  But at one point what</p>
<p>00:20:12 would happen in gym classes was that we had gym maybe three or four times a week and we would play basketball or as they would say some calisthenics in basketball.  And then part of the class for white kids would go down to the pool and they would swim or learn to swim.  And blacks were not allowed to use the pool except on alternate weekends</p>
<p>00:20:58 when the sexes or the black woman or girls would use the pool after the class and then the pool was cleaned.  And on the other weekend the black boys would use the pool and then the pool was cleaned out.  And there was a ruling from the Supreme Court of New Jersey that all the facilities had to—could not be segregated, that all the school facilities had to be</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0006">0006</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>00:21:48 opened to all people.  And armed with that knowledge I decided I was going to use the pool.  I don't know how I learned it, I must have read it in the newspaper.  And what made the</p>
<p>00:22:16 story so observed—</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  [interposing] Tell what you did.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Huh?</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Tell what you did, tell what the only one—</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  I read about it and what made it so observed was that I couldn't swim and I would have to go—I would go to the pool every day that</p>
<p>00:22:50 was gym class when the white boys went down.  Once I went then the white boys stayed out of the pool, nobody was in the pool but me and I couldn't swim, I was scared to death even in a few feet of water because I didn't know.  And I was in the pool alone during the class.  I couldn't get any other blacks to join me.  And after that semester you know that I</p>
<p>00:23:30 was threatened by the teacher, they were going to expel me and stuff and I refused to - - they pleaded with me to not do this, to stay on the floor like the others.  But my feeling was</p>
<p>00:23:55 that I was entitled to use that pool and that it was my right to use it.  If I had been right at that time, even if I couldn't swim was not the issue, they would be teaching me to swim.  They were teaching white kids who couldn't swim, that was the time they were taught then to swim.  So it was a very stressful time for me.  And that result was that instead of</p>
<p>00:24:44 allowing everybody to use the pool and opening it they closed it.  And it was a bad feature for the school, East Orange because it had one of the best swimming teams in the city.  It was winning all the tournaments and stuff like that.  But it decided that instead of opening the pools to everybody that it would close it.  And that showed me the great cost to</p>
<p>00:25:25 whites of segregations, they pay a price for it.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Okay.  You enrolled at Lincoln University in Pennsylvania when you were 16.  How did you come</p>
<p>00:25:43 to go to Lincoln University?</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0007">0007</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Well I skipped a lot of classes, I was considered very bright.  And I was a very good test taker.  So I would finish by testing before anybody else and leave the class.  Now I don't—you know what I always considered prayer and like I said I can accept that.  But it seems to me that that's a gift too, being</p>
<p>00:26:32 able to learn to take tests well and that does not necessarily mean intellectual gift but at the time because I was so good at it, I was considered intellectually gifted and all accept that no point - - now.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  What was Lincoln like?  Lincoln University.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Hmm?</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  What it like to be a</p>
<p>00:27:06 student at Lincoln University?</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Lincoln University was a great experience for me.  I really had such a wonderful time there.  It was isolated and off the green path</p>
<p>00:27:43 and we spent a lot of time together, my friends and I, and played.  While I was not interested at that time in the hard sciences.  What I was interested in was the social sciences and while I was in the laboratory and so forth, I'd be looking out wanting to be on the campus playing ball and all this stuff.  It was really one of the very great times in my life. I</p>
<p>00:28:46 was so—you know had friends and people there because we were so isolated.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  It was the first time you were in a predominately black educational environment.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Yeah.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Did that have something to do with it?</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Yeah, we were.  What I</p>
<p>00:29:12 learned however was that it was not the school, it was a time when I had all my friends and people there and I went back sometime later with the—you know the - - was going.</p>
<p>00:29:42 INTERVIEWER:  How did your time at Lincoln prepare you for Civil Rights activism do you think?</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0008">0008</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  When we were—Lincoln was an all male school and its professors were former professors retired from Princeton.  And the head of the - - or whatever he is, of Lincoln was a Princeton graduate and they never—the Lincoln men at that</p>
<p>00:30:56 time very boorish, would get drunk and tear things down and so forth.  And there was no effort to curb this.  And when we came along we thought that this was—they were being paternalistic, that the faculty was, that they sort of condoned this as a way that had to be accepted because blacks were not able to control themselves.  So my generation the</p>
<p>00:31:43 school felt that we should be able to control ourselves, we didn't have to be breaking up things and stuff like that and we were young men, supposedly educated and so we should</p>
<p>00:32:12 not tolerate this boorish behavior that was being - - and accepted.  So we started agitating for black faculty, for more blacks on the faculty.  There was only one professor, an English black on the faculty, all the rest of the people were white.  And we again agitated for that.  And I think—and we was on the debating—I was on the debating</p>
<p>00:32:56 team and we had debates with the small colleges like Haverford, not the Ivy League schools and colleges but just below that.  And I think what that did for me was to enable me to not fear competing with whites.  That gave me some courage and understanding that I could compete with white people which was one of the problems at that time with the</p>
<p>00:33:47 blacks all had because they were stereotypes, were worried about being able to compete with white people.  But that was a good time in my life that I remember.  It was helpful.</p>
<p>00:34:13 INTERVIEWER:  That's important.  How did you come to choose to go to Howard Law School?</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  How did I come—</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  From Lincoln you went to Howard, what—</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  I went to Howard Law School on a scholarship.  One of the people was recruiting and I had never thought I could be a good lawyer</p>
<p>00:34:47 because of my voice, I don’t have a good voice and I thought a good lawyer had to have a big voice and you know they claim and stuff.  But I found that I didn't have to do that to be a decent lawyer.  What you had to do was to be able to know the facts and to be able to be convincing with all the facts and the law.  And my idol was William Hastie who was</p>
<p>00:35:28 the Dean of Harvard Law School and he didn't have a good voice but he was very, very smart and knew all the facts.  And I came to realize that when I had a law—a case that what I</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0009">0009</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>00:35:52 had to do was know all the facts, be convincing with all the facts so that I could answer all the questions.  And that I didn't have to decline.  That helped me to become aware that I could be a good Civil Rights lawyer.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  And what was it like to be a law student at Howard University.  You enrolled in 1937 in the fall.</p>
<p>00:36:28 JUDGE CARTER:  Well it was—at the time Howard was on a special mission.  Charles Houston had a program that we were going to fight segregation, the separate but equal does on the Plessy versus Ferguson.  And we were going to fight it by making all the institutions that, state institutions that offered courses for whites and not for blacks to offer duplicate</p>
<p>00:37:36 courses for blacks or establish separate schools for blacks.  And we knew that they couldn't do that.  And finally what happened was that as we fought to make them offer these</p>
<p>00:38:03 separate courses, we realized that they could not pay for it and so they began to, in the graduate school, they began to accept blacks without segregation.  Or they would do as they did in my first case that I argued before the Supreme Court.  The separate but equal doctrine, in this case McLaurin they tried to provide the separate but equal doctrine.</p>
<p>00:38:51 McLaurin was in the same class and the same faculty, all his segregation was that he was required to sit in a special seat and he was required to use a separate table and he had maybe a rope around him but this is was considered really separate but equal.  And this was the beginning of the precursor to Brown.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  That's right.  Because</p>
<p>00:39:54 you won that case.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Yeah.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  That was in 1950.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  That was my first case.</p>
<p>00:39:59 INTERVIEWER:  Right.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  And the Supreme Court held up the separation to provide him of the ability to learn his profession.  And that a separate school—that's a separation itself to provide him of the ability to learn.</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0010">0010</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  But let's go back to Howard just for a little bit because that's down the road a bit.</p>
<p>00:40:33 JUDGE CARTER:  Back where?</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Back to Howard when you were a student there.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Howard.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Because while you were a student you mentioned Charles Houston.  You mentioned Charles Houston and while you were a student at Howard he tried the first major case that would be part of the cases</p>
<p>00:40:49 leading to Brown, the Gaines case.  And you were there to see that.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Yeah.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  And also came to Howard the day before for Moot Court.</p>
<p>00:40:59 JUDGE CARTER:  Yeah.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Could you tell that story about Moot Court and then going to the Supreme Court and watching him try that case.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Well my first time I was in a Supreme Court building I heard his argument before the Supreme Court in the Gaines case.  This guy Missouri ex rel. Gaines was seeking</p>
<p>00:41:48 equal educational opportunity and they had a school for Gaines on a—they had the school in Gaines for blacks and no school for whites as I recall.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  So if you want to start by the University of Missouri, the Gaines case at the Supreme Court.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  I think the Gaines case was the first argument that I</p>
<p>00:42:53 had witnessed in the United States Supreme Court.  And there were two things about the case as I recall that became a tradition.  The day before the argument we had an</p>
<p>00:43:21 argument at the school, the law school, and in the course of the argument Charles Houston argued the case.  One of the Justices asked Mr. Houston a question that one of the students in the - - were argued before us had queried, had asked, and that made all the Supreme Court arguments brought by the—on the NAACP offices and the legal defense fund,</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0011">0011</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>00:44:16 those arguments were made to Howard Law School the day before they were argued by the Supreme Court.  And that became a tradition for a long time.  And that was—we got a lot of run with that and heard people—Houston and Thurgood and I, we always argued these cases the night before and that was that.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  So how was Houston in</p>
<p>00:45:06 the Supreme Court?  What was it like seeing Houston argue the Gaines case in the Supreme Court and being there?</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Well I got—I was always sort of nervous at first and</p>
<p>00:45:21 then would get involved in the argument and I'd lose it but—</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  [interposing] Yeah, but watching Houston argue the Gaines case, what happens in that instance?</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Houston argued the Gaines case and in the course of his argument, when the case was called, Justice McReynolds turned his back on Houston throughout his argument.  And</p>
<p>00:46:00 the story goes, it's probably not true, that after the case was over that Justice McReynolds had his—his barber was doing his hair and he said that I just heard the nigger Houston argue a case in the Supreme Court.  And so the barber turned to him, this is the story, and said that Mr. Houston we consider him one of the great people and we think he is</p>
<p>00:46:55 capable and qualified to sit on the Supreme Court.  And if he did we know that he would represent all the people and not just a few.  The story goes that as they told that that</p>
<p>00:47:18 McReynolds became slumping in his chair.  I don't know whether it's true or not but I hope it was.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  That's a great story, that's great.  Any just quick impressions of Charles Houston, could you describe—</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  [interposing] Quick impressions of who?</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Impressions of Houston</p>
<p>00:47:38 that you had.  Impressions of Charles Houston as a person, anything stand out to you?</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0012">0012</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Impression of who?</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Of Charles Houston.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  He was an informable guy.  I didn't know him very well.  I only heard him argue a few cases because, or one or two cases, because he I think had money problems and he</p>
<p>00:48:21 could not stay with the NAACP.  He had to—he turned to that job over to Thurgood because he had a child, a son I think, and he had to go - - and make some money.  So I was not—Hastie</p>
<p>00:48:53 was my icon, I know Houston too well.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  He was your mentor.  The other big event that happened during your years at Howard Law School was on Easter Sunday in 1939.  When you were among the group that—</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  - -.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  And you had a job that day to do, you were working in a restaurant and you made a decision.</p>
<p>00:49:22 JUDGE CARTER:  Well I had a scholarship to law school but I also had a part time job, first as a busboy and then as a waiter to make some extra money and also to help pay—help me - - my school.  And so I waited tables.  And the Marian Anderson concert, Eleanor—they refused to allow her, the Daughters of the American Revolution refused to</p>
<p>00:50:21 allow her to sing in Constitutional Hall.  So Ms. Roosevelt arranged for her to sing at the Lincoln Memorial.  And that day it was a day that I asked to be off but I was refused of</p>
<p>00:50:53 course and I hoped that I wasn't going to be a waiter for life and I knew that wasn't going to—so I just went to the concert and it was memorable.  Everybody was half in tears and I cried, because I cry easily, and she sang beautifully and it was historic.  When I got back to the hotel the dining room was in chaos and so you know I got it</p>
<p>00:51:53 straightened out and after the evening meal was over I was fired as I would have expected to be.  It was - - so they fired me and I was not unprepared for that.  But what happened after I was fired was that I got a full scholarship to the—because I work in the library part time and so I worked in the library and did my lessons and stuff like that and was</p>
<p>00:52:55 worked, got money for that and so the whole thing was a boost for me.</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0013">0013</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Could you describe a little bit more being in that crowd?  What was so moving about being at the</p>
<p>00:53:10 Lincoln Memorial?  What did it look like?</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Well we all knew that history was being made and she was in great voice and here this black woman was at the Lincoln Memorial singing how they segregated the Daughters of the American Revolution, she had desegregated Constitutional Hall.  And they wanted—kept the segregation</p>
<p>00:54:03 of the Constitutional Hall but after that they were out of the picture because that was why Mrs. Roosevelt got Marian Anderson to sing at Lincoln Memorial.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  And the crowd was integrated, it was all—</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Oh yeah, it was a big, big crowd as I recall.  Everybody was in tears, at least I was crying,</p>
<p>00:54:34 because we thought history was being made.  This woman was in such great voice and the first black woman to sing before this large integrated crowd.  It was a huge gathering, it</p>
<p>00:54:58 was a historic day.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Great.  When you graduated from Howard you went off to Columbia on a scholarship.  What were your plans leaving Howard Law School?  How did you see your future?  And why did you go to Columbia?</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Well I had not really focused on—I had worked at the NAACP and I thought that I had explored to</p>
<p>00:56:00 the limits and there was nothing else I—</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  [interposing] Well let's back up because you didn't go to the NAACP until after the war.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Huh?</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  You didn't go to the NAACP until after World War II.  You went to Columbia on the Rosenwald Fellowship.</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0014">0014</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>00:56:19 JUDGE CARTER:  Yeah.  I was on a scholarship working on first amendment issues and I had my thesis that I was working on was the extent to which the right to—first amendment</p>
<p>00:57:00 rights were essential for the democratic process.  And it got me very excited about it and during that time when my thesis, when I decided I was going to work on this, I had two avenues.  I could work fulltime on that issue and take a few classes and I would be able to get my Doctorate because I was working on a Doctorate - -.  I could get my Doctorate after</p>
<p>00:58:06 a year's residence and I had five years to complete it.  I could complete part of my dissertation.  Or I could take a whole lot of courses and get my Doctorate—my Masters in law that way.  The more difficult route was to write part of my thesis and I was advised by the faculty to take the courses that the other way was more difficult.  And that annoyed</p>
<p>00:59:01 me and so I decided that I was going to work on my thesis and try to finish it and have it accepted.  And I chose incorrectly, my advisor I chose Noel Dowling who in my class</p>
<p>00:59:35 and the law school, he had read the text and he was—what shall I say, he was one of these technicians who felt that the Supreme Court differences were based upon this slight change and a little change in this and that, not on the social scene outside the court.  And I felt that was nonsense.  But I also felt that I learned from him that in arguing before the Court</p>
<p>01:00:03 it did sometimes did you good to make these little distinctions because the Court would find a way to rule for you without making an overwhelming ruling.  And that I learned although my feeling was that the Supreme Court's changes followed the vote and that political change was reflected in the Supreme Court's rulings.  But in the process of getting a case, a</p>
<p>01:01:29 ruling with a case, it was good to be able to argue this little distinctions because it helped the Court, I realized, make a ruling without admitting that it was</p>
<p>01:01:46 politically affected.  And so I learned, I learned a lot from that.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  The next one, when we get to World War II and I'll just ask you how did World War II impact your life.  And that's a good question, don't you think?  And start out by saying World War II because they're not going to have my questions in your tape, they're just going to have</p>
<p>01:02:22 you talking, so either repeat the question—</p>
<p>[END afc2010039_crhp0001_mv1]</p>
<p>[START afc2010039_crhp0001_mv2]</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0015">0015</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  And I think the point to emphasis is the part you didn't resist the draft you went in at—describe how you entered the Army/Air Force and your involvement on World War II, its impact on you.  Just pick</p>
<p>1:00:24 up where you were just now.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Now?</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Yeah, pick up in the summer of 1941, you did not resist the draft.</p>
<p>01:00:33 JUDGE CARTER:  Well at the time I had thought that I had gone as far as I could go and regarding segregation I thought that there was nothing else to do.  That I had exhausted all the avenues of fighting segregation and I was restless and here I was also of some age and I didn't feel comfortable or that I had anywhere in my career, I was worried about what I</p>
<p>01:01:30 could do in my career.  And so I didn’t resist the draft, I thought that if I got in the Army it would improve my health and all that sort of thing, which it did as a matter of fact.  And when World War II broke out, Pearl Harbor and so forth, I was in the Army.  And it came at a time when NAACP was arguing and fighting for blacks to become a part of the</p>
<p>01:02:42 Army and not be just a servant.  And up to that point they had not had these black people, there were a few black units, all black units, but they hadn't had all these blacks be</p>
<p>01:03:10 integrated into the Army.  And it presented a problem to them because they hadn't had a core of black men trained for anything, they were all the long time people who had been in the Army were people who were not well educated people, they had operated as servants to white men, to white officers, and then men like they were staff sergeants and so</p>
<p>01:04:05 forth but these were the only blacks who had any standing and experience and so these blacks became the people that they utilized as to take in and train and discipline all these new blacks that were coming in.  The NAACP and other people were very concerned about that and their agitation for them to train black people, to these black recruits to</p>
<p>01:04:58 get opportunities to become officers and so forth.  And it was in that setting that I became a part of the Army, Army Air Corps it was called at the time.  We had no training, had</p>
<p>01:05:25 this sergeant who was ignorant who was a staff sergeant and what we did for the most part—what they had us doing for the most part was clearing bush, we went to Augusta, Georgia and we were clearing trees and cutting down trees and clearing them.  And I knew I wasn’t going to—that that wasn't for me.  So I wasn’t a lawyer at the time, I had a lot of legal</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0016">0016</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>01:06:09 education but I hadn't passed the bar, that didn't mean anything.  The staff sergeant who was now in charge of these black recruits in Augusta and so forth was an ignorant long time Army man.  He had a couple of wives, had all kinds of problems and so I became his lawyer and I represented him, advised him about his domestic problem and as a result</p>
<p>01:07:06 I was given—I was not in the workforce clearing bush, I was in his office as his advisor on various aspects.  And then I had a problem—I want to say I had a problem with</p>
<p>01:07:46 Hayes.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Well I think the detail is interesting but really what's so important is how your experience in the Army set you on the course of your life as a civil rights lawyer.  I mean the kind of racism you experienced, you just said before off tape that it was devastating.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Well what I knew at</p>
<p>01:08:11 the time that I was not going to spend my time cleaning brush and that sort of stuff that I had to find out where I was at.  And so I became this man's personal lawyer and represented him.  And after the agitation of the blacks for the open Army to—so for black recruits to be able to become officers and so forth that agitation opened a way for me to get to officer</p>
<p>01:09:11 candidate school.  And I became a member of the Quartermaster Corps.  And the Army was then as I recall segregated but we—within the Army that was segregated but within the</p>
<p>01:09:47 Army we had our exercises and so forth we worked in tents and as I recall there were maybe 10 blacks and we were all in a tent together.  But then we took classes and drills and stuff with—after Truman, our call for integration—</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  [interposing] No.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  No?</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  No, that's '48.  You</p>
<p>01:10:22 leave the Army in '44.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Okay.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Well here's what you write, I want you to react to this.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  I was in the Army in—</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0017">0017</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  [interposing] You said it was the Army experience that made a militant of me.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  I was in the Army and what bothered me about the time about</p>
<p>01:10:46 the Army then I recall was that segregation was so much a part of it that whites enlisted and had no respect for black officers and they wouldn't salute and so forth.  And I</p>
<p>01:11:14 brought an action against several of them, against them for not treating me with respect.  That was one incident.  I think there were three incidents that occurred during that period of time that made the base officer accuse me of trying to riot, of causing a riot, me alone.  And my theory was that at that point—now I'm getting ahead of myself.  I was no</p>
<p>01:12:26 longer enlisted what I'm talking about now.  I'd gone to officer candidate school I think and I had become an officer and I wasn’t given any respect.  So at one point in the course of—I was on the base and they offered me the right to live off the base and I said I had no right to live off the base, I wasn't married, I had no intention and I was not</p>
<p>01:13:26 entitled to live off the base.  And in the course of my being on the base, one night an officer came in the barrack and he was saying to me that this is one hell of a place and</p>
<p>01:14:03 I said he wanted to—I don't know he wanted something from me.  And I was about to get to—what the hell did he want, he was looking for—he was looking for—</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Hanger.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Huh?</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  He wanted a hanger.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Yeah.  He was looking for a hanger for his clothes and I</p>
<p>01:15:18 wanted to give him one and I said I would.  And he said this is one hell of a place because he couldn't find a hanger.  And I said it certainly is and that set him off.  And he stopped and started screaming, "Who is this nigger?"  And it was dark and he came up to me and I saw that he was a lieutenant colonel and he said to me when he saw I was an officer, second</p>
<p>01:16:06 lieutenant, he said I'm your superior by many grades and when you are supposed to be—to rank on your senior officer on another grade and you're supposed to acknowledge that or</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0018">0018</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>01:16:44 something like that.  And I said, "You may be my senior officer by many grades but what you have to do is learn some manners and when you learn some manners I will be able to respect you but in the mean time get the hell out of my room."  And he was furious.  And the next day I saw him in the latrine washing up and he had on his shorts and he was naked except</p>
<p>01:17:29 for his shorts and I reported him his exposed body when he saw me he got red as a beat.  And he could have court marshaled me or tried to but I think that he was afraid he couldn't win that battle because he knew that he had been discourteous and that was my time in the Army.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Okay.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  The thing I—that was</p>
<p>01:18:21 an incident that really set me off and then I—let me see, I brought charges against a couple of white enlisted men because they didn't show me any respect and the officer, the</p>
<p>01:19:01 base commander, was handing the business that he was from—and so forth but you know things were changing time.  And I couldn’t revolutionize things right then and there.  And I told him I wasn’t trying to revolutionize things but I thought that as an officer I was entitled to respect.  And I intended to get it or I was going to go fight</p>
<p>01:19:48 in Washington.  He wanted me to live off the base, I didn't want to live off the base.  So I was then very soon transferred.  At one time in the officer's club—I told you this didn't I?</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Tell the story.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Just told it to you.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  No you didn't tell the story.</p>
<p>01:20:22 JUDGE CARTER:  I was in the officer's club and it was at a bar—that was sort of a bar.  And white officers of course were there.  And I went up to the bar to ask for a drink.  The</p>
<p>01:20:52 bartender was a black man and looked as frightened as I felt because I had to walk what felt like a gauntlet.  And I ordered a drink and he said he didn't know whether he could serve me.  I said well why, I'm an officer, why can't you serve me.  He said blah-blah-blah.  And so he finally said that okay and poured me this drink.  But then I couldn't pay in</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0019">0019</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>01:21:37 cash, there were chips that I had to have and he couldn't accept the cash.  One of the other white officers standing by told him to put it on his bill.  I thanked him and I finished my drink.  And that ordeal was so devastating that I never tried it again, it was just too much for me.  I should have gone back but once was enough.</p>
<p>01:22:19 INTERVIEWER:  So summing that up then, how did you experiences that you just told us about, how did that affect how you felt when you came out of the Army and what you did with</p>
<p>01:22:30 your career?  How did the Army change you, how did it draw you to the NAACP?</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Before I went into the Army I was at Columbia and I had these friends and so forth and I almost had the feeling that segregation and discrimination were not really issues because I had all these friends around and we were</p>
<p>01:23:28 friendly together and did things together.  And that if you worked hard and so forth that you could beat the system and so forth.  And fortunately for my well being I went into the Army and the hatred against black soldiers was so vicious and prevalent that it was good, it opened my eyes that I realized that segregation was a real thing and that</p>
<p>01:24:19 you had to fight it.  That was a good lesson for me because I really had almost come to the conclusion that discrimination, if you worked hard and so forth you could live in this</p>
<p>01:24:44 country without discrimination bothering you.  And then I became to understand as I went into the Army that being uneducated you were discriminated against, being educated didn't save you from the viciousness of discrimination.  And that was a very, very good lesson for me.  And when I came out of the Army I was determined to fight segregation and</p>
<p>01:25:29 to devote my life to that and that has been my motivation for the rest of my life.  The amazing thing though is that now the Army and the Air Force are institutions in this country that are more nearly acceptance of diversity and equal opportunity than any other institutions in the country.  And that's the amazing thing how that</p>
<p>01:26:26 institution has changed.  The Air Force and the Army are now places where blacks are as able to get equal opportunity as any institution in the United States.</p>
<p>01:27:00 INTERVIEWER:  Well let's get you in the NAACP.  The next part is how you get into the NAACP, you come out of the Army in 1944, how do you end up working in the NAACP?  And you come out with this commitment.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  I came out of the Army and I really was a very country bumpkin and I knew nothing about the NAACP's tradition.  I hadn't heard of</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0020">0020</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>01:28:10 Thurgood, I hadn't heard of Hastie, I was from East Orange and the NAACP and Roy Wilkins and those people, I never heard—I had never heard of them.  When I came out of the Army, I guess because I was—I had gotten into trouble in the Army because I refused to accept segregation and I was fighting segregation and talking about it.  And some of the Army, I</p>
<p>01:29:46 got in bad, bad with the Army officials because they took me on to be a snitch.  I was supposed to report to the officers all of the trouble makers and the thing that was</p>
<p>01:30:16 so amusing was when they found out that I wasn't—you know I had a liberal newspaper delivered to me and so—but somehow I wasn't going to be one of those who was going to be snitching on the other, I was probably making trouble and complaining and stuff myself.  And the officers began to cause me a lot of trouble.</p>
<p>01:31:17 INTERVIEWER:  Well we've already did the Army stuff.  You come out and you reconnect with William Hastie, wasn't that what happened?  You reconnected with William Hastie when you came out of the Army?</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  What about - -</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  You reconnected with William Hastie when you came out of the Army.  But that's not so</p>
<p>01:31:41 important, we don't have to do that.  I mean you went to work for the NAACP in 1944.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  I been--worked for the NAACP.</p>
<p>01:31:48 INTERVIEWER:  Yeah.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  When I was discharged from the Army in '44, Bill Hastie was the Dean of Howard Law School and he told Thurgood to start to recruit me because he thought I would be good on his staff.  And I went on his staff and then I got drafted.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Again.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  And I had trouble with</p>
<p>01:33:16 the Army—I told you all this.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Yeah.</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0021">0021</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  We don't need to go over this again.  And when I settled my problems with the Army I followed Hastie's advice and sought—even though I was now free, I had my honorable discharge and I was free of the whole thing, I followed his advice and saw the war wasn't over</p>
<p>01:34:14 and sought to rejoin the Army in some capacity.  And I was turned down by the as then general, with thanks but no thanks.  And I think I wasn't a good solider but I think I could have</p>
<p>01:34:47 been a better one if I had been allowed to be sort of—have some freedom of action and not have to face all this nonsense.  But it was an experience that affected my life.  And I got out and decided I was going to spend my life fighting discrimination.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  So at what better place than the NAACP.</p>
<p>01:35:31 JUDGE CARTER:  Yeah.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  So what happened, you're hired and what were you hired to do?</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  What?</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  What were you hired to do at the NAACP?</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  I was hired at the time when the NAACP at Howard University was on a special program.</p>
<p>01:36:09 And that program we were designing cases to desegregate state institutions.  And the issue was for us to train a cavalry of black lawyers that would go into</p>
<p>01:36:43 institutions, back to their home town and fight discrimination.  Bring cases and so forth and so on on discrimination.  And that was the program that Howard University carried on for some time.  At first the whole purpose of the program was to find state institutions that—in the separate but equal doctrine and Plessy versus Ferguson that offered</p>
<p>01:37:39 gains or goods or services or education for whites and not for blacks.  And these lawyers under Houston's program were to bring litigation to force white institutions to either set up programs and accept blacks or be faced with litigation.  And that continued for quite awhile.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  What your relationship</p>
<p>01:38:32 with Thurgood Marshall because at this time he was heading it up, Houston had gone back to Washington.</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0022">0022</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Well my first—I remember the first with Thurgood—</p>
<p>01:38:52 INTERVIEWER:  1944.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  My first contact with Thurgood was I was on his staff and I was sort of given a—because I had all this education, I was given a little cubby hole for myself.  And what I was supposed to be I guess, the domestic guru.  And the rest of the staff was in a bigger room and I had this little cubby hole to myself.</p>
<p>01:40:05 And at one point we had to get a briefing—we were on a case, the separate but equal doctrine in Gaines, I think it was in Gaines.  We were on a case—no, yeah.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  No, Gaines was 1938.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  I was to write a brief, no.  We had to get this brief in and—which case was that.  Thurgood was out to lunch and I was told by</p>
<p>01:41:40 his secretary to do this brief and I was very reluctant to do it because I thought that I shouldn't be authorized.  And they had long lunches and stuff and when he got</p>
<p>01:42:03 back the brief was done and he looked over it and sent it out.  And from that time on I began to be the guy who was doing the briefs and things like that behind the scenes.  I did that for a long time and I did not have my name on them and things like that, it didn't matter to me.  But after awhile I began to feel that I should get some credit for—</p>
<p>01:42:58 INTERVIEWER:  [interposing] So you would—okay, all right.  In addition to that—so you're really running the litigation program, writing the briefs, but you also traveled a lot as an NAACP lawyer.  You tried cases in every state in the South.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Yeah.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  And you have a description of what that was like.</p>
<p>01:43:22 Can you talk about your travels in the South and going into these courtrooms where black people would come into watch.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Well when we had cases</p>
<p>01:43:39 at that time they were public theater.  The first case, like teacher salary case, Constance Motley and I tried to try that case.  This was the first time they had seen a black woman lawyer in Mississippi.  And the people were ecstatic because we were putting the superintendent on the hot seat and they were reenacting our courtroom drama as we explored</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0023">0023</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>01:44:51 with these people under cross-examination, put them on the hot seat and everything like that.  And they would reenact all this stuff in the barbershops and stuff with us.  Constance Motley was the first black woman lawyer in Mississippi to argue a case.  And now of course I'm sure that black woman are common place, are arguing cases in Mississippi and</p>
<p>01:45:36 every place else.  But she was the first black woman they had seen and they were just amazed that this black woman with her New England accent and stuff was arguing this case.  And now</p>
<p>01:46:08 that's common place.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  So people would crowd into the courtrooms, African Americans would pack the courtrooms when you'd go in to try a case.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Well that was during that period of time they would.  In the Federal Court there was no segregation, they wouldn't allow it in court.  State court there was but</p>
<p>01:46:44 the blacks were so crowded and white people wanted to get in but they couldn't compete with all these black folks and so in the most part they were out in the corners listening.  But in the Federal Court they didn't allow that, that segregation and so blacks filled out the courtroom and as these things were enacted.  And Connie would tell the—or asking</p>
<p>01:47:31 Thurgood or I would be asking questions and at some point the white superintendent wanted to ask me a question or Connie a question and the audience would laugh, I would say no,</p>
<p>01:48:01 I ask you the questions and you respond.  It's not your role to ask me to respond to questions that I put.  And you know the audience it was vicarious, the audience was so bothered down with segregation, it's human nature.  But that vicarious - - lives through us or through us this joy of being able to put the questions and put white</p>
<p>01:48:45 superintendents who fostered segregation on the hot seat.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  And then you'd hear word that they'd reenact that scene?</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Yeah.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Can you say that again, you would hear that they what?</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Hmm?</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0024">0024</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  You heard word that the people in the community would</p>
<p>01:49:06 reenact.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Yeah, they would reenact this stuff in their barbershops and beauty parlors and all over town.  That was a very</p>
<p>01:49:23 interesting era.  But after awhile it was no longer the theater that it used to be.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Yeah, it moved outside.  What was it like traveling in the segregated south as a young lawyer?</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Well I didn't have too much difficulty.  What you did when you traveled for the most part, you had no hotel facilities, after awhile</p>
<p>01:50:30 you did have decent facilities.  But as I recall when I argued the Topeka case, one of the first of the Brown state cases, Jack Greenberg and I had to stay in a hotel and this was an awful hotel and I thought—told Jack that he didn't have to stay there, what he should do is stay at a decent hotel, he refused of course.  But subsequently we began to find some</p>
<p>01:51:36 decent accommodations.  But at first it was just awful to find some decent place to stay and eventually at times we stayed with black friends.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Families.</p>
<p>01:52:04 JUDGE CARTER:  Yeah.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Your first case before the Supreme Court was the McLaurin case, you mentioned that earlier, can you describe that case and what that experience was like going before them?</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  As I remember the McLaurin case—</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  [interposing] Actually</p>
<p>01:53:03 you described it.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  McLaurin was—this was called separate but equal.  McLaurin, he couldn't say he didn't have the same facility.  He had the same facility, he was required to sit in a special seat and he was roped off from his classmates in a special lunch place and so forth.  But he had the same books, the same professors.</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0025">0025</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>01:53:54 We argued that he was denied equal educational opportunities because he was segregated, he was not permitted to have intellectual intercourse with his fellow students.  We really had a</p>
<p>01:54:27 problem with some of our public about that because some of the people felt that we were carrying it too far, that we certain to lose because the separate but equal doctrine was being played out before us and they felt that the differences were too insubstantial for us to win the case.  And Thurgood was very politically astute.  He brought these cases and</p>
<p>01:55:23 made public statements and so forth about them.  And did so to not allow the people who were supporting segregation to have the day.  And although each time he proves correct the Supreme Court in our favor, the next time—you know the next case they said we're going to far because the Supreme Court is - - substantial and so forth.  But he was a good</p>
<p>01:56:12 publicist, he knew how to handle the cases like that.  And it was really a very great time for me.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Okay.  In June of 1950 you talked about equalization, trying</p>
<p>01:56:38 to push Plessy to its limit, but in June of 1950 the lawyers decided to attack Plessy directly.  Can you talk about that shift in strategy and the significance of it?</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  It was really sort of a half shift because we told our people that we were going to take only cases—that we were going to attack segregation per say as being</p>
<p>01:57:31 unconstitutional and that we were not going to concentrate on unequal facilities although we did as a backup, you know, to show unequal facilities.  But our main thrust was that segregation per say was unconstitutional.  Because our theory was that the states could equalize or try to equalize the facilities or close the gap.  And they might win.</p>
<p>01:58:28 So we had to argue that segregation per say was unconstitutional.  At the same time we were also arguing about unequal facilities so we didn't really give up the unequal facilities</p>
<p>01:58:48 argument that was a fall back on plan.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  But here's where your role is so important, bringing in social science and Kenneth Clark, can you talk about your role in the development of strategies for challenging Plessy?</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  For challenging Plessy?</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0026">0026</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>01:59:09 INTERVIEWER:  For challenging segregation in the schools.  How were you going to make the case that separate could not be equal.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Well I was—the first step was Charles Houston's thesis out there was to bring all these cases and make them too expensive for the states to maintain.  And the theory was that they would then have to</p>
<p>02:00:06 allow blacks in the white institutions.  And if they did that at the graduate and college level then they would be clear nothing would happen.  It would be clear that</p>
<p>02:00:30 segregation was quickly maintained peacefully and there wouldn't be riots and all that sort of stuff.  So that was what we first began doing and then when we came to the high school and so forth level.  When it came to the grade schools we didn't have the luxury of faculty to rely on.  We didn't have the luxury of the exclusiveness of alumni, we didn't</p>
<p>02:01:29 have all those things we had in the graduate schools and so forth.  All the schools were presumably one like that, there may have been some specialized grammar schools but for the most part they were supposedly all the same.  And this was when Brown versus the Board came up and we had to argue that segregation per say was unconstitutional.  That it</p>
<p>02:02:16 impaired the ability of black children to learn and we began that—</p>
<p>[END afc2010039_crhp0001_mv2]</p>
<p>[START afc2010039_crhp0001_mv3]</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  So we're going to pick</p>
<p>00:00:33 up with that.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  We were preparing a case in Claredon County to segregating the schools and Otto Klineberg who was the Chief Social Scientist at Columbia University, at the Social Science department at Columbia University.  Had made a study which showed that black migration from the segregated schools</p>
<p>00:01:18 in the South to Philadelphia then integrated, that the longer they stayed in the Philadelphia system out of segregation the higher—</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  [interposing] On integration.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  —they scored on tests, on oral matters that measured their educational ability.  We were then about to bring the case seeking to</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0027">0027</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>00:02:13 attack segregation in Claredon County, South Carolina schools and I went to Klineberg and told him what we were doing and said that his study was exactly the thing we needed.  I</p>
<p>00:02:52 was a black man and he of course was initially leery of getting involved because he didn't know where I was coming from.  But what he did say to me, no I'm not going to help but he referred to Kenneth and Mamie Clark.  And I went to—I heard of them and their work and I went to them and told Kenneth what we were doing and I asked him if he could help us.  And</p>
<p>00:03:53 at that time they had made Northside Center for Child Development, the only institution of its kind in Harlem, was sought to test the segregation's impact on black children.  And Kenneth and Mamie had devised this doll test.  And the doll test was very, very provocative, I guess.  They would show a black doll and a white doll to children, the</p>
<p>00:05:20 good doll, bad doll.  The bad doll was always black, the good doll was always white.  But the confusion was that the white doll was always them, the child who was being interviewed.</p>
<p>00:05:41 And so the theory was that they thought about was the impact of segregation and discrimination on black children because that it impaired their ability to learn and gave them a sense of inferiority.  I believe that the Clarendon County case was the only case that we used this test in presentation.  We went to South Carolina and rented a house</p>
<p>00:07:17 where we could work and get prepared for the trial.  And one of the incidents that was very funny was that when the train left us off in Charleston, South Carolina, Kenneth was running saying where are my dolls, where are my dolls and Spottswood Robinson who was one of our people heading out then apprised of what we thought of doing and he</p>
<p>00:08:15 was looking at me missed because he thought Kenneth was kind of—and he got himself together when we told him what it was all about.  But I think that was the only case that we</p>
<p>00:08:41 actually used the doll test itself.  And tested the children and had them testify.  Other times or instances we had sociologists talk about it on the witness stand.  What happened when Kenneth joined forces with us and became in fact almost a member of the staff was that he was able to get professional witnesses for us to testify in various cases and so we</p>
<p>00:10:12 didn't have to rely on one or two people to become professional witnesses, we had a whole bevy of people we called on to testify as experts for us.  And one of the things that I assisted on with these people was not to try to help us by testifying out of their expertise, stay within it.  Don’t try to help us by testifying the things that they</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0028">0028</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>00:11:01 couldn't support.  And when the academics learned that we began to—they began to relax and so like in the classroom they realized that they only had to testify about what they</p>
<p>00:11:24 could support and back up.  And thus they relaxed and were very good witnesses because I said to them when you go outside you field you are not doing us any good because what all the lawyers try to do is for the period of time of the cross-examination and stuff for the case, it's to learn as much about your expertise and your views and how to</p>
<p>00:12:08 cross-examine you for that moment as an expert, when you try to become an expert like you.  And so you don't do us any good if you don't keep within your area of expertise.  Because if you do, you're not helping us at all.  When the academics learned that was what we wanted them to do, they relaxed, testified in their field and didn't get beyond that.  And so we</p>
<p>00:13:08 were able to—all people were able to stay well within their area of expertise.  And what happened several times was that experts on the other side sought to testify outside their</p>
<p>00:13:36 level of expertise and when Kenneth helped, you know was advising me at the cross-examination, we were able to make them pay for it.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Could you say a little bit about how innovative the use of social science was in the Brown case and how—</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  [interposing] Well—</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  —important it was to</p>
<p>00:14:09 the decision.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Yeah.  Well when we came to try to use the social science data in Brown and we got the social scientist to file a brief showing that segregation was harmful, some of the people on our committee were very dubious because it was not part of science.  And what Thurgood allowed me always to do is he allowed me to</p>
<p>00:15:18 go as far as I could as long as I could support it.  And so some of our advisors didn't go for the social science stuff because they said it wasn't hard science and they</p>
<p>00:15:38 didn't believe in it.  And I said to them well I have nothing else and if you want to offer an alternative, fine.  But if not I'm going to take this risk and that's how social science got into it.  And Bill Coleman who was one of those that felt that the social science was not hard science came to agree that it was excellent.</p>
<p>00:16:38 INTERVIEWER:  It was the key.</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0029">0029</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Kenneth?</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  No, it was the key.  It was the key to Brown, social science.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Yeah.  It was the key in the Brown case.  But it was the case in Topeka that essentially it came out, the three cases that we were arguing segregation per say.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  And could you state the</p>
<p>00:17:32 majority opinion of Brown, what it said, how it ruled in overturning segregation in the schools.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Well Brown held that—we argued I should say, that equal</p>
<p>00:17:52 educational opportunity had never been argued in an education case.  That it had been assumed by a lot of lawyers and judges that equal education opportunity had been argued and initially in the Supreme Court.  But what we were able to show was the Court had never looked at it initially, it had assumed that other courts had initially looked at this -</p>
<p>00:18:56 - but that had not been so and so we argued that what the court ought to do now is to look at the separate but equal doctrine and Plessy versus Ferguson as never being argued in a equal education case.  And looking at it for the first time that separate but equal was unconstitutional.  And that was Chief Justice Warren brought that argument and wrote the opinion</p>
<p>00:20:12 that we had indicated and that was the Brown case.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  And it really is based on the social science, they grounded their opinion.</p>
<p>00:20:25 JUDGE CARTER:  Yeah.  This was the first use of social science.  And we had social science people writing a brief in support of the issue that segregation per say was unconstitutional.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  What was your expectation when the Court ruled unanimously in Brown?  What would happen?</p>
<p>00:21:01 JUDGE CARTER:  I came to the conclusion that the Court argued that the Court reached unanimously and Brown won on the thesis that it would be unanimous but the implementation would be as they said with all deliberate speed, whatever that meant.  And the implementation meant that segregation was, back in Topeka, the first case that the Topeka did</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0030">0030</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>00:22:08 not school, did not want—they didn't want to argue the case, they wanted to get out of it, they were ready to concede.  And the Supreme Court—I wanted the Supreme Court to hold in</p>
<p>00:22:41 Topeka that segregation per say was unconstitutional.  But since they decided that they weren't going to meet that task the Court said it was moot and didn’t reach the issue.  And I proved correct because when the all deliberate speed came out it took some 10 or 20 years before Topeka again reached the point that it was willing or ready for this</p>
<p>00:23:40 segregation.  When the all deliberate speed issue came then the Topeka case continued and the woman or the kid or the child who had brought the case initially and the city or the state did not want to hold it moot and the Supreme Court did and some 20 years later they were still fighting of that case.  Until I think they held more recently or decided to hold more</p>
<p>00:24:46 recently that the time for all deliberate speed had run out.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  And throughout the South you had massive resistance in response to Brown.  And you really</p>
<p>00:25:00 didn't have meaningful school desegregation in the South until after 1968 or 1970, 71.  So how do you—what is the significance of Brown?  Is it just about schools?  How do you see the significance of the Brown decision in '54—</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  How do I what?</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  The significance of the Brown decision.</p>
<p>00:25:27 JUDGE CARTER:  Well the significance of Brown was its holding that segregation was unconstitutional.  And it had significance because after a long period of time when it had sort of run out and the all deliberate speed business was gone that we had to hold that segregation itself was illegal.  And the state finally came to that path.  But the</p>
<p>00:26:34 problem was that if it had held that without all deliberate speed indication we would have been long gone.  The all deliberate speed business delayed, delayed and delayed</p>
<p>00:26:55 because nobody knew what all deliberate speed meant.  Or what it meant apparently was that you could just delay implementation of Brown, of the decision.  And the significance to me on Brown was that segregation was per say unconstitutional, that enforced segregation with law is no longer viable in this country.  And although</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0031">0031</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>00:27:57 we still have segregation it is segregation that people are accepting but that it is not enforced by law.  And I think that at some point is the time is going to come when it's going to be this public, at least I hope so, this public forum to end sort of voluntary segregation which the country is engaged in the present time.  We don't have segregation by</p>
<p>00:28:56 law anymore but people are still segregated and keep themselves segregated and we don't have a public urge to end it.  So that is going to—the beauty of the present is that at</p>
<p>00:29:30 some point there's going to be this public push to end segregation.  And since there's no law to enforce it that with the voluntary segregation, I'm hoping it's going to reach a point where it will not be viable.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  A few more points to cover with the important role you play beyond Brown in addition to working for enforcement is that in</p>
<p>00:30:15 the South the backlash to Brown, trying to shut down the NAACP, trying to outlaw the NAACP.  You were able to draw on the work you did at Columbia to fight that and do you want to talk about that first amendment—</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  The problem was that when Brown was decided there was a backlash against the NAACP.  We had</p>
<p>00:31:02 not been bothered because the southerners didn't feel that we worth bothering with, you know NAACP.  But when the Brown case was decided they went after us on the thesis that if</p>
<p>00:31:26 they could outlaw the association that would end the problem for them.  And so I had to spend a lot of time fighting to keep the NAACP alive in litigation because we were being attacked in various states, they tried to outlaw us, they tried to do this and that because it's unconstitutional and so forth and so on.  So I had a jurisprudence</p>
<p>00:32:15 protecting and fighting for the NAACP life because southerners felt that if they outlaw the association that would end the problem.  They didn't realize that the association was not the issue that the people were concerned with it and outlawing the association they'd have to outlaw other folks who under some other name would be fighting to end segregation.</p>
<p>00:33:11 Universe—Alabama versus NAACP, one of the cases in the Supreme Court which sought to hold that the NAACP was—that holding NAACP right to fight segregation as being unconstitutional</p>
<p>00:33:55 and we had to bring cases to show that we had the right to seek equal educational opportunities free of state coercion.</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0032">0032</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  And you won?</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Yeah, we won that case.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  And that was important for all civil rights organizations.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  - -.</p>
<p>00:34:25 INTERVIEWER:  That was important for the rights of all civil rights organizations to function.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  That was a very important case.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  And then NAACP versus Button?</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  NAACP versus Button, another very important case which sought to hold that the NAACP—outlaw</p>
<p>00:34:56 the NAACP.  And we were able—the Court held that we had a right to join together in the association, to peacefully seek equal educational opportunities free, that was our</p>
<p>00:35:24 first amendment right.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  And one final major point but I think it's important is your decision—you become General Counsel of the NAACP in 1955 and you make a decision to turn attention to the North and to the problem of school segregation in the North.  Could you say a bit about why you did that and how you attempted to apply</p>
<p>00:35:54 Brown beyond the South?</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Well I—let me see how I can say this—can get this.  I had a problem with—Jack Greenberg and I had a problem.  When Thurgood left Jack wanted to take Thurgood's place and be the head man and reduce me to the role of counsel.  While he ran the works of Thurgood's, took over Thurgood's role and my role was just</p>
<p>00:37:32 to be counsel for the NAACP with no right to bring segregation—the segregation cases and so forth.  And he tried to get Roy to bar me from bringing segregation cases, that they</p>
<p>00:38:05 all should come to him as head of the legal defense fund.  And we had a very, very fight, public fight about that.  He sought to get Roy to turn—have me turn over to him all the segregation cases.  And I was very bitter with him because in the beginning he had been so helpful with me on segregation cases and then when Thurgood left to go onto court, onto</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0033">0033</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>00:39:38 Court of Appeals, he thought that as counsel of Thurgood's successor that he could have Roy bar me from bringing any of these segregation cases and they all were supposed to belong to him.  The problem with that was that I had all the segregation cases, I had them in my hand and I was certainly not going to turn them over to him.  He thought he could get</p>
<p>00:40:33 Roy to do that, to force me to do that.  And Roy was very—probably Roy was not willing to have a public fight and he knew that if he tried to accept Jack's plan that there was</p>
<p>00:41:17 going to be hell to pay.  And that's how Jack Greenberg and I had our problem with one another which now, you know, I left the association because they fired Lewis Steele who was a member of my staff without notice to me, without consulting me, because he had written an article and the article came out unfortunately on a day that the NAACP Board was</p>
<p>00:42:30 meeting and its title was Nine Men in Black who think White.  And I was told that Thurgood was on the Court at the time and he was furious.  And as a result of that article they fired Lewis.  And I threatened and my whole staff threatened to resign if they didn’t reinstate him.  Fortunately Roy was in Paris and wasn't able to - - this stuff, so it</p>
<p>00:43:33 all came out and the ACLU and I was resigning and I got a halo, think w here I'm a black man with a pretty good job and I'm resigning my job because they fired a white boy.</p>
<p>00:43:54 The opposite of the stereotype.  And so at that point I was sort of tired, I didn't know where I was going with the school segregations because I thought I had exhausted all the avenues.  But when I threatened to resign if they didn't reinstate Lewis, I began to get revitalization because I thought for the wrong reason because here I'm black and I'm</p>
<p>00:44:57 resigning a pretty good job because a white man has been mistreated.  So that gave me a new lease on life.  It probably helped me get a judgeship too I think because I don't know how I—I was first come up to be a judge when Thurgood—in the Kennedy era, Thurgood was wanted to a judgeship and they were ready to give him one but only at the District level and he</p>
<p>00:46:17 wanted something bigger than that.  And the Kennedy didn't, at that time, feel that blacks were—this was too good of job for a black man so they came after me.  And I had these</p>
<p>00:46:51 people that wanted me to get a judgeship and Adam Clayton Powell and I had several conversations and he indicated to me that I had to pay, if I paid a certain amount of money for the judgeship I could get it.  So I told my advisors this and all hell broke loose because they felt that was a big to do and stuff like that.  And it ended up with my people had to</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0034">0034</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>00:48:07 back down because of the politics of the issue.  And I always say that I was responsible for Thurgood getting his Court of Appeals appointment because all the hell-a-boohoo that was caused by my people that Powell had asked me for money or indicated that I give him money in the end it was politics.  He had the votes and so I was abandoned and that ended up</p>
<p>00:49:16 with Thurgood getting it.  And I thought at that point that my chance of getting a judgeship had ended but several years later that kind of passed.</p>
<p>00:49:40 INTERVIEWER:  But before I finish up I just want to go back one more time on this school piece because when you left in 1968, when you left the NAACP you were involved in the Ocean Hill-Brownsville case, in the Harlem 201 case and I think your fight for equality education for black children sort of was beyond Brown.  You tried to look to the North and deal with</p>
<p>00:50:08 the problems with segregated and unequal schools in the North.  So maybe if you'd want to reflect on that, on the state of education today what's happened and what hasn't happened, but your efforts in the North were really pioneering.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  The North schools were—what I discovered about the North was that the issue of</p>
<p>00:50:38 segregation was not North/South it was nationwide and the northern schools didn't want integration, they wanted to keep their schools segregated and they were</p>
<p>00:51:06 gerrymandered in instances.  But the northern school segregation is—that the northern issue of segregation is no different than the South.  The issue of keeping blacks and whites separate is a national phenomenon.  And there has been no push recently to move and I expect that at some point there is going to be an issue of this manly voluntary school</p>
<p>00:52:23 segregation.  I don't know but right now everything is—nobody is doing anything publically and the issue is dormant.  But I'm hoping that at some point there is going to be a push for someone to end voluntary segregation, to make it more of a public issue again.  But so far nothing.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  One last question and then we'll do our filling in.  In the</p>
<p>00:53:15 light of your history and your long struggle in the civil rights movement, how do you see the significance of Obama's election related to your history and to the</p>
<p>00:53:29 struggles you've been involved in?</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0035">0035</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Well there's been several things that have happened with Obama that were unexpected.  And the passage of one of the bills for equal education, one of the bills that Obama managed to get through came as a shock and surprise.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  But just the actual election of Obama we were all here</p>
<p>00:54:36 that night, just his election, how did that make you feel in terms of your work to break down barriers to get voting rights in the South, I mean nationally, any thoughts on that moment?</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  Well I think that his election was certainly supportive of what I had hoped to achieve.  But my story and what I hoped to achieve was</p>
<p>00:55:31 not the election of a black president, I wanted to still achieve equal educational opportunities in fact for all, for the poor, for blacks and so that everybody had a</p>
<p>00:55:55 chance at equal educational opportunities because I think that that's the key to finding black equality and diversity.  And for me however is if everybody was able to secure equal educational opportunity it would be so.  Now that may be an elitist's view, I don't know, but that's how I look upon it.  And I am now too old to pursue it because I'm</p>
<p>00:56:52 not one of those people or try not to be who wants to stay on the stage long after I've been useful.  I think that I've had my time and that younger people ought to come after me and there are a number of them who I think are going to take it over.  So I don't have any sense of trying to keep these folks—I encourage them to come on because I have—I'm sort of</p>
<p>00:58:01 mentally fatigued and sometimes I have—I do a little writing and stuff like that but I really haven't done anything of any substance for a period of time.  I might get</p>
<p>00:58:35 stimulated to do something but I don't know.  My feeling is maybe.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Well you've done this.</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  But I think—I chafe at vegetation and sometimes I get weary of it but I am not one to go back.  If I get stimulated maybe I'll do some writing and stuff but I don't know.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Ready.</p>
<p>00:59:48 JUDGE CARTER:  George McLaurin, I think his name was George.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  George McLaurin.</p>
      <pageinfo>
        <controlpgno entity="Page0036">0036</controlpgno>
        <printpgno/>
      </pageinfo>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  —applied.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Start again, start from the beginning.  George—</p>
<p>JUDGE CARTER:  George McLaurin applied to the University of Oklahoma Graduate School and was given many of our—the public felt was the epitome</p>
<p>01:00:25 of separate but equal because he was taught by the same faculty, in the same class, all he had was a separate seat in the lunchroom and the classroom and that was sought to be</p>
<p>01:00:47 the classic separate but equal doctrine of accept but it proved vulnerable.</p>
<p>INTERVIEWER:  Great, that's good.</p>
<p>[END afc2010039_crhp0001_mv3]</p>
<p></p>
<p>Irvine,  CA Ubiqus Reporting, Inc. New York, NY</p>
<p>(949)  477 4972  (212) 227 7440</p>
<p>www.ubiqus.com</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</tei2>


